<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A spirituall purgation sent vnto al them that laboure of Luthers errour as touching the bodely presens of Christe our sauiour in the sacrament, and to al them that haue espyed the libertie of the gospel as touching theyr fleshe, yet seke not the lybertie to make free theyr spyrite from thys afore sayde errour.</title>
            <author>T. C., fl. 1548.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 126 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B11902</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4312</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103887</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839629</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839629</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4069</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B11902)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4069)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 524:6, 1528:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A spirituall purgation sent vnto al them that laboure of Luthers errour as touching the bodely presens of Christe our sauiour in the sacrament, and to al them that haue espyed the libertie of the gospel as touching theyr fleshe, yet seke not the lybertie to make free theyr spyrite from thys afore sayde errour.</title>
                  <author>T. C., fl. 1548.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[160] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [W. Hill for] Hugh syngelto[n] at the sygne of saynt Augustyne in paules churche yearde],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1548?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; actual printer's name from and publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>At foot of title page: Cum priuilegio ad imprime[n]dum solum.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-K.</note>
                  <note>Formerly also STC 20510.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 20510 on UMI microfilm reel 1528.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; Cambridge University Library copy on reel 524 lacks I4 and is tightly bound affecting text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the originals in the Cambridge University Library (reel 524) and the Bodleian Library (reel 1528).</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 524 (Cambridge University Library copy) and at reel 1528 (Bodleian Library copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Real presence --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lutheran Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4069:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4069:1"/>
            <p>¶ A ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all purgation ſent vnto al them that laboure of Luthers Errour, as touching the bodely preſens of Chriſte our ſauiour in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to al them that haue eſpyed the libertie of the goſpel as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching theyr fleſhe, yet ſeke not the lyber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to make free theyr ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite from thys a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſayde errour: Ihon. xviii.</p>
            <q>¶ Euery one that is of truth heareth my voyce.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum Priuilegio ad imprime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dum Solum</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4069:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4069:2"/>
            <head>To the right worſhypfull and godlye Knyght, Syr Thomas wyat, thee Auctor hereof wyſſhet helth &amp; encreaſe of grace to perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in chriſt oure Lorde. Amen.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as moch as the accoſtumable vſe of this our realme after the long ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſens of our fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des returned into theyr natyue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, we ſemed than with gyftes and preſentes the only ſygnes and tokens of theyr affectyon towardes them, right worſhip full knyghte. I vnable to be a frend, yet of lyke affectyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyl,
<pb facs="tcp:4069:3"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:4069:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4069:4"/> and hart, as frendes are, haue addreſſed thys poore and rude preſent to welcome you wythe all, whyche coueteth not fame or eſtimacion that commonlye telleth the myndes of men, but that thing only, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I knowe you to be to your power, a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender &amp; maynteyner namelye the glory of god &amp; truth of his moſt ſacred wordes the earneſt of our ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Partly therfo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re moued by affection &amp; dutye for your benyuole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s towardes me, and chieflye for the hartye zeale you beare vnto the moſt ſacred goſpel of Chriſte Ieſus I am ſo bold to dedicate thys, rude and vnlerned, yet ſymple and true lucubration.</p>
            <p>Whom I hartelye deſyre you to accept at my poore handes, not lokynge vnto the gyft, but
<pb facs="tcp:4069:4"/> vnto the mynde of thee geuer, not forgetting the ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tylnes of Artaxerkices Kynge of Percia who refuſed not a draughte of colde water at the handes of a poore labourer, conſyderynge his hart &amp; not the baſenes of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> gyft. Thus doyng ye ſhal ſhar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any deſyre hereafter, to vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyte you wythe ſoche lyke, my poore exercyſes. Thus y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lorde god of myght and euerlaſting power encreace you wyth hys grace and augment your knowledge in hys gloryous Goſpell, AMEN.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4069:5"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The boke to the Chriſtian reader wiſſethe helth grace &amp; vnderſtandinge in the Lorde Ieſus.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Yke as the chyld doth ſore lament</l>
               <l>And greuouſlye take hys mothers lake</l>
               <l>Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo am I not wel co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</l>
               <l>Myne authors ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des thus to forſake</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And as the chyld ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not wythſtand</l>
               <l>Hys parentes wyl, but muſt obeye</l>
               <l>So lyeth it not within my hande</l>
               <l>My authour wil, to agayn ſaye</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But the prouerbe in very dede</l>
               <l>Thys dout briefly doth ſo diſcuſſe</l>
               <l>Nedes ſhal y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> muſt wyth haſte &amp; ſpede</l>
               <l>The matter in no caſe can refuſe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4069:5"/>
               <l>Syns, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther is no remedy</l>
               <l>But forth to troge and haſt to make</l>
               <l>To ſlacke the tyme it were but folye</l>
               <l>In thys y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> I haue vndertake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Helpe haue I none me to vpholde</l>
               <l>In thys greuous perplexitie</l>
               <l>But god whych biddeth me be bolde</l>
               <l>Hys truth to ſpeake &amp; veritie</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which is of force I know ryght wel</l>
               <l>Me to mayntayn in euery caſe</l>
               <l>Agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> clergie &amp; byſhoppes cruell</l>
               <l>That thus gods worde ſtyl do deface</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whoſe tyranny &amp; fylthy pryde</l>
               <l>Whoſe doutfull table Epicuriall</l>
               <l>Whoſe welthines and myters wyde</l>
               <l>Whoſe golde ringes moſt cynedicall</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Hath gods own word i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoch diſdayn</l>
               <l>And there at doth ſo ſwell and freate</l>
               <l>That it to colour they cannot refrayn</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4069:6"/>
               <l> It caſteth nought therin to ſweate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Theyr ſuppoſal &amp; grooſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iecture</l>
               <l>Not ruled by the teſtament</l>
               <l>They place in ſtede of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſcripture</l>
               <l>Agaynſt the Lordes ſpiritual entent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whych thing amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt the multitude</l>
               <l>As a Scorpio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mooſt cruel &amp; fel</l>
               <l>Hath ſtong theyr hartes both blynd &amp; rude</l>
               <l>And drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr fayth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the goſpel</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So that they now in places clatter</l>
               <l>Autoritie hath taught vs ſo</l>
               <l>As for the goſpel it maketh no matter</l>
               <l>Be it wel, or be it woo</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus recheles in deſtreinte of mynd</l>
               <l>They preferre mens blynd fantaſye</l>
               <l>Contrary to the nature &amp; kynd</l>
               <l>Of godes worde and verytie</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wherfore as one y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> doth lament</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4069:6"/>
               <l> This ſore diſeaſe and malady</l>
               <l>My brothers conſcience to haue rent</l>
               <l>And fylled it wyth myſery</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I haue prepared thorow gods good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes</l>
               <l>For this vnkynd perturbacyon</l>
               <l>To the mynd a gentyl releaſſe</l>
               <l>Called a ſpirituall purgatyon</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whoſe nature is to mudyfy</l>
               <l>And cleane eſchoure the conſcience</l>
               <l>Of them whom luthers hereſy</l>
               <l>Hath infecte wyth the bodyly preſens</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of chriſtes body in the ſacrament</l>
               <l>Vnder forme of bread ſtyl to remayne</l>
               <l>Cleane contrary to the hole concent</l>
               <l>Of gods holy ſperit &amp; word certayne</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wherin they maye as in a glaſſe</l>
               <l>Theyr errour trye and take awaye</l>
               <l>Pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g theyr hartes i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> libertie &amp; grace</l>
               <l>Of oure hygh god the aſſured ſtaye</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:4069:7"/>
               <l>Of all mankynd that faythfully</l>
               <l>Vpon hym cal wyth feare &amp; tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blyng</l>
               <l>He is theyr lord &amp; guyde truly</l>
               <l>That wil the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lead in this good lerni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So that errour &amp; fantaſye</l>
               <l>And gredy lucre apt to reache</l>
               <l>Shal not ſeduce the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo fondly</l>
               <l>Agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> truth, this vntruth to teche</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wherfore good reader I y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> requyre</l>
               <l>In peruſyng me be pacyent</l>
               <l>Syns that the prophete is my deſyre</l>
               <l>And goddes glorye is my hole intent</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who hath me framed verely</l>
               <l>For this purpoſe an inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</l>
               <l>Only to publyſhe his glory</l>
               <l>And the truth of hys holy Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And not to pleaſe the carnal eye</l>
               <l>Or ſatiſfie the vnkynd luſt</l>
               <l>Of our pote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; mighty clergie</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4069:7"/>
               <l> Whych ar nothyng but aſſhes &amp; duſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That ſo ſtoutlye in euerye place</l>
               <l>Defend theyr wicked tradicyon</l>
               <l>Diſhonorynge the ſperite of grace</l>
               <l>To theyr mooſt ſhamfull confuſion</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Except they do forſake theyr ſynne</l>
               <l>And repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of theyr wyckednes</l>
               <l>Theyr ware to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyll neuer wynne</l>
               <l>Any yote of the lordes ryghtuouſnes</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whych is our fort &amp; ſauing helth</l>
               <l>Our ſtrong towre &amp; treſorye</l>
               <l>On who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth al our welth</l>
               <l>Exempting vs from myſerye</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Vnder whoſe holy protectyon</l>
               <l>Mekely to walke is a ſolas</l>
               <l>which leadeth to the blyſful ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſion</l>
               <l>Of endles ioye &amp; laſting grace</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thorow chriſt our lord &amp; ſauiour</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:4069:8"/>
               <l> Our ſacrifice and ſatiſfaction</l>
               <l>Of Iſrael the only redemer</l>
               <l>In who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the faythful haue ſaluacion</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To whom be prayſe glory &amp; honour</l>
               <l>Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t dominion continually</l>
               <l>whych reyneth wyth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father of equal</l>
               <l>Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> age to age perpetually power</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>AMEN</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:4069:8"/>
            <head>Grace mercy and peace of conſcience be vnto all them from god the father, thorow our lord Ieſus Chriſt, which faythfull ye wythout colour obeye the truth in ſetting forthe goddes glory. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Rother, for aſmoch as our heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the mouthe of his true ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Paule, hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded al his adoptiue heyres pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted in him by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
               <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>cious death &amp; croſſe of our ſauiour chriſt, to exerciſe theyr tonge (who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God hath created to magnyfie hys name) in Gods holy &amp; moſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred word, willi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> no other
<pb facs="tcp:4069:9"/> word ſhuld procede out of our mouth, but that which ſhal edi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fye whan neade is to geue gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce to thee hearers, &amp; greue not the holy ſperite of god by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ar ſealed in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> daye of rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion: Our diſobedience ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not <note place="margin">Ephe, iiii,</note> be hydde from the ryghtuous iudge, which wayeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> though<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, &amp; ſercheth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reynes of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s hart, yf we which couet this fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhyp &amp; ſocietie of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god, go about not onlye to burden weakelin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges wyth errours dampnable, but alſo to greue y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> holy ſpirite of god thorow our vayn drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes or Imagina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, beleui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge creatures before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> creator, whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>refore good brethren dylige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly marke you my wordes and not myne, but the wordes of the ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyng god, whych are not ſente to you at thys tyme for rebuke
<pb facs="tcp:4069:9"/> rebuke or occaſion (God I take to wytnes) but for loue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you ſhulde not be pertakers wythe the Ipocrites whoſe porcyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is <note place="margin">Apoc, xxli</note> leyed vp in the lake of hel, bur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning with fyer and brymſtone, but for this cauſe they are ſent vnto you aſſuredlye, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lyke as you whyche entende to leue in goddes feare haue ſought a re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demye for the imperfectyon of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> fleſhe, &amp; frayle nature of god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des word, yf ye haue learned to ſatiſfye it according to his wil without ſynne: euen ſo to helpe your weake iudgementes, and your vnperfight ſperit (as tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed body &amp; blood of Chriſt our ſauiour, you may repayre vnto his word of him ſeking &amp; pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge with the prophete, that he wyl eſtablyſhe your iudgemen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes
<pb facs="tcp:4069:10"/> in hys truth &amp; make your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes ſaue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wycked me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they ouerthrowe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not. For whan ye ſought a pheciſion to eaſe your ſycke fleſſhe, &amp; to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chardge you of a carefull bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; paynful yocke, that a law papiſtical had layed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your necke, you councelled not thee chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the world were they neuer ſo famous, no not mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Luther, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be nothing elles, of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelf, but vanitie &amp; lyes the prophete beareth you witneſſe ſaying. Man is vpon the waughtes lyghter tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie it ſelfe. And in another place. All me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ar lyars, but you councelled him who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you knew could not lye, becauſe it is tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the it ſelfe, &amp; conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pneth lyars ſaying. I wyl deſtroy all them <note place="margin">Pſalm. v</note> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſpeake lyes, &amp; therfore you
<pb facs="tcp:4069:10"/> were ſure that y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> libertie which ye now poſſeſſe, was good, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted it that could not be reproued: Nowe moche more ought ye, for the diſceate that troubleth your ſoule, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely falſe iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; erroure which is the beſt part of you, vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your bodi muſt both obey and ſerue not to ſticke to fleſh &amp; blood, which by vngod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly lyui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ar robbed of true iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gement in the miſterye of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des truth, but as y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſperit being the beſt parte of youre bodye, who beyng lyghtened, your bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perſeuer in darkenes: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo goo ye vnto him, which is mooſt chiefeſte &amp; myghty in operacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> able to make y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> blind to ſee, the deffe to heare, the do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me to ſpeke, &amp; to heale the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des that errour hath maymed
<pb facs="tcp:4069:11"/> you w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>al, nameli goddes word, for hit al thinges were created, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out it nothing was created no not luther, whom al though gods ſperit ruled to ſpeke ſom thinges right, yet wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to loue hym ſelf &amp; ſet forth hys owne dreames not ruled by the ſperit of god, he erred as ſome other of hys forefathers hathe done, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this ſower leue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being but litle in qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>titie, yet in qua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>litie poyſon ſharpe, hath as the ſcripture ſaith, ſowred his hole lompe of dowe. But good bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren ſyns ye ſtand fre, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſhe, &amp; that by goddes word, be ye not bound in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite to the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, call rather to your remembraunce, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as the potter excedeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pot, the workema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the worke, &amp; thee
<pb facs="tcp:4069:11"/> creator thee creature: Euen ſo the wyſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god our creator &amp; not only ours but luthers alſo excedeth our wyſdo &amp; Luthers too. Whoſe folyſhnes is more wyſer than the wyſdom of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wherfore as wiſdom wold let vs repayre vnto him whych is hole wyſe, hoole good, &amp; truth it ſelf, that he may by his word open your eyes, that you may knowe your diſceate &amp; be hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the Goſpell, Whyche as paule ſayth is y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> power of god <note place="margin">i, Corin, i.</note> vnto ſaluacyon to all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that beleue it. And who ſo denyethe <note place="margin">Iohan, iii</note> it, he is already conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned for therfore are we called the ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of god becauſe we haue be <note place="margin">Gala. iii</note> leued in Chriſte Ieſus, whom god the father hath by his ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſperite ſealed as wytneſſeth Eſaye the prophete to preache <note place="margin">Eſaye. li.</note> vnto
<pb facs="tcp:4069:12"/> this goſpel namely deliuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnto the captiue &amp; healinge of the ſycke mens woundes, only that al they which beleue thys mooſt ſacred word denying vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>godlines ſhuld be made a righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuous plantinge wherein god ſhuld reioyſe. For god hath cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led vs by his mooſte glorious goſpell not to allowe the Ima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginacion of fleſhe eyther to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyet our conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce according to theyr opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, polluting our faith whom hathe choſen to be his ſpouſe with y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> adulterynne dregges of carnall wyſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we knowe leadeth vnto death. For Paule ſaith to be carnally <note place="margin">Rom, viii</note> mynded is death: but to be ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rituallye mynded is lyfe: For carnall wiſdom ſauoureth not of god which is a ſperit &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped in ſperyte &amp; truth, and therfore it is vnable to iudge
<pb facs="tcp:4069:12"/> of the word whych is ſperite &amp; lyfe to them that ſticke therun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to with fayth vnfaynedly, and therfore let it not defyle oure ſainctuarie &amp; faythfull ſperite vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god wyl declare the ſe myſteryes that are aboue y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> grype of fleſhe, for as a louing huſband poſſeſſing a faythful wyfe, whoſe propertye is to be ſilent, doubteth not to commu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nicate hys ſecretes vnto her, becauſe his loue ſhuld appere Euen ſo our meſſias hath not feared to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate the miſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ries of his truth vnto a lowlie ſperit &amp; ſymple hart, whom he hath maryed vnto him ſelf, by the lyuely fayth whych we ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue in the merites bloud &amp; wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des of the anointed ſauiour to this witneſſing y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> prophet Oſe as, ſaith in the perſon of god I <note place="margin">Oſee. ii</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:4069:13"/> wyl marrie the to me in fayth, and thou ſhalt knowe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I wyl be the lorde, Wythoute fayth, therfore as it is vnpoſſyble to <note place="margin">Eſay, vii. Hebre. xi</note> pleaſe god, as Paule wryteth: ſo is it vnpoſſible w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out it, to enter, to enter y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> depth of gods truth. And therfore ſayth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phet. The wrath of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord came vpon Iſrael, becauſe they bele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued <note place="margin">pſal, xviii</note> not in God, nor truſted in hys ſauing helth. Agayn wo be to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſſolute harte, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beleueth not god, nor truſted i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ſaui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g helth, &amp; therfore, ſhalt thou not be defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of hym: But vnto y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> apoſtels whych in faythe were moued to him, he ſayd with his own mouth. It is geuen vnto you to know y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſecretes, miſteri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es of the goſpel. Why? becauſe ye haue not take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wyſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be your ſcholemaſter, but by a
<pb facs="tcp:4069:13"/> ſymple hart, forſaking ſyn, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſperite of god to be your guyde. As for an example what ſcholemaſter had Natha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niel wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> fyrſt ſyght he ſaid <hi>Rabbi, tu es ille filius dei, tu es ille</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iohan, i<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>Rex Iſrael,</hi> that is to ſay. Good mayſter, thou art that ſonne of god, thou art that kyng of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell. What moued Peter to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe Chriſt to be the ſonne of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lyuing god, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of fleſhe &amp; bloud, ſondrye wayes Propheſyinge of hym. Doubteles men taughte them not thys doctryne, but the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of God, whyche ſpake in them, and to thys Chriſte hym ſelfe beareth wytnes ſayinge. Bleſſed arte thou Symon Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter. <hi>Quia caro et ſanguis non</hi> 
               <note place="margin">math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i.</note> 
               <hi>reuelauit tibi, ſed pater meus qui est</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4069:14"/> 
               <hi>meus qui eſt in celis.</hi> For fleſhe &amp; bloude hath not reueiled vnto the: but my father whiche is in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Contrary wyſe what in ſtructour had the high preſtes and Phariſies whan they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led hym Carpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ters ſonne Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maritan &amp; Beelzabub, ſayinge in thee name of Beelzabub he dyd caſt forth deuyls. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les fleſhe and blood, which poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeſſe not (as Paule ſaythe) thee Kyngdom of God. <hi>Quia carna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus ad eſt zelus &amp; contentio &amp; ambulare ſecundum hominem.</hi> Becauſe fleſſhiynges ar ful of <note place="margin">i. Cor. xv. i, Cor. iii.</note> conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion &amp; ſtryfe, to walke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mans doctryne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Therfore ſay I that god hath not called vs by his holy Euangelion to determyne our fayth vpon the dreames of men, for fayth is a perfecte gyfte, &amp; al gyftes that
<pb facs="tcp:4069:14"/> are perfect &amp; good done, come from god whych is perfyghte, and therfore they are not to be eſtablyſhed vpon me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which ar without the grace of our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly father al vnperfect and ſynne, but rather vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> goddes truthe. For what a blyndenes were it (good brethren) to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade our conſcyens to know the myſteryes of gods truthe, thinking that we poſſeſſe a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie infallible: wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſo ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſticki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vnto the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of earnall men, blaſpheme the truthe, what greater blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye, I pray you can there be more, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> opynions of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which be for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> moſt part w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſperite of god more lyes &amp; fables, ſhall out of the boſome of his creatures, ſhutt out the truth of our mooſt hye god, in
<pb facs="tcp:4069:15"/> whoſe lippes Dauid fayth, the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re was neuer foundgile, &amp; ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le vp theyr eares leſt thei ſhuld heare the comfortable embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of peace who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Paule calleth in the epyſtel vnto Tim. profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table doctryne, ſaying. <hi>Euange lium gloria dei, quod creditum eſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Timo. 1</note> 
               <hi>mihi ſana doctrina eſt.</hi> The Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gelions of thee glorie of God, whyche is delyuered vnto me, is an holeſome doctryne. And alſo vnto the Theſſalonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s he wryteth <hi>Verbum accepiſtis a no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bis, non vt verbum homine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſed ſi</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Theſſa, 1.</note> 
               <hi>cut eſt Vere verbum dei.</hi> (that is to ſay) Ye haue receaued of vs the word, not as y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> word of men but as it is in dede, the word of god. Agayn vnto Tite he wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thus, encoraginge hym in his endeuor. <hi>Verbu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, irrepre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>henſible</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4069:15"/> 
               <hi>loquere, quod non blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemetur omnia,</hi> that is to ſay, <note place="margin">Titum. 2.</note> Speake the holeſome &amp; faure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe word which wyl not blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme at al. Now brethren de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely beloued, yf ye obey vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truthe, Euen as Ezechiel was moued of god, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the ſtubbernes of the Iſraeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, to preach &amp; teache this his word, &amp; ſharpely to reproue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theyr frowardnes, in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſawe hys wonderfull worke, &amp; yet beleued not, neyther tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from theyr wyckednes, to declare hys vnmeſurable mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye that he wolde all to knowe and noo man to peryſſhe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughe erroure, ſaythe. <hi>Verba mea loqueris ad eos, ſi forte au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diant &amp; quieſcant, quoniam irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarores ſunt,</hi> (That is to ſaye). <note place="margin">Ezeche. 2,</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:4069:16"/> Thou ſhalt ſpeake my wordes vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that yf it wyl be, they <note place="margin">Ezech. ii.</note> may geue eare, for they ar men that prouoke me Euen ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the ſperit, I wyl yf god be pleaſed, ſet hys word before your eyes, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> thereby you maye perceaue the mercye &amp; grace of our heauenly father, that he is not wylling to ſe you peryſſhe thorowe thys your abhomina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble errour, euen the word that is of power able to ſaue youre ſoule. Caſt away therfore thes myſtes and cloudie pha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taſyes of carnal iudgemente, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching this word (For god hath ſayde, my thoughtes are not your thoughtes, nether yours ar myne,) And deſyre hartelye with me that the holy on of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell may ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your gates, that the kyng of glory may enter in
<pb facs="tcp:4069:16"/> ther at to diſcuſſe by hys holye ſpirite the truth of thys youre doubte, that your weake co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ens may no longer wauer and be compelled to hange vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But that you maye not only haue vnderſtanding in thys, but to ſeke hys glorye whych hath to al them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue the goſpell reueled lyfe, &amp; <note place="margin">ii, Tim, i.</note> immortalitie, the power of Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tan, hell &amp; death, beyng vaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyſhed, yf you ſhal ſe for hys truth ſake both confute youre errour, &amp; breake in ſonder thee baſtelio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whoſe walles ar built with vnte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pered claye, and ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore as a tottering wall muſte come to nought: Frayte not your hartes wyth diſdayn, wil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lingly thorowe malice procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring your own deſtrucito<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but as the word loui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly exhorteth
<pb facs="tcp:4069:17"/> you, be meke and lowlye to hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re thee worde of God, that you <note place="margin">Eccle, v.</note> maye vnderſtande, and brynge forth a wyſe and true anſwere. For euery worde of God is pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re (as the wyſeman ſaythe, and <note place="margin">Prou, xxx</note> a ſhyld of defence to them that put theyr truſte in hit. For aſſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re thy ſelfe that he cannot be of God, whych preferreth the dur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye dregges of mens braynes, before goddes word, for as Io<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>han ſayth, euery one that is of <note place="margin">Iohan, 19</note> God, heareth the truth, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye one that heareth truthe, heareth god. For my ſhepe hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re my voyce, and I knowe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and they folow me, nether ſhal any of them peryſſhe, nor noo man ſhall take them out of my hande. Ieremy the prophet, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe he wolde not haue vs ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by anye fonde Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion, forbiddeth not only to <note place="margin">Ierem. 23</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:4069:17"/> heare thoſe prophetes, that pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pheſye theyr own dreames, but alſo ſayth in the voyce of oure heauenlye father, Take hede, <note place="margin">Ierem, 7</note> that ye herken not to councels which i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deuour to diſceaue you, and to do you no good. Nowe yf you wyll trye your ſelues to be as ye wold be reported, aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de in the word, and then ſhal ye be partakers of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> promes that god hath made by hys worde, that is, ye ſhal know the truth and it ſhal make you fre, for he <note place="margin">Iohan, 8,</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is of God, heareth his word.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He diſciple the fyrſt <note place="margin">Exodi, 12,</note> day of ſwete bread came vnto Chriſte ſayinge, where wilt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> that wee prepare for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, the eaſter or paſſouer la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be to eate, for it was accoſtumed a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Iſraelites, that they y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4069:18"/> fyrſt moneth &amp;. xiiii. day of the ſame at nyght the houſhold of thee Iſralites ſhulde thorowe oute all theyr coſtes &amp; borders eate no leuened bread, but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuened vntyl ſeuen dayes we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re clerely expired? And further that in the daye of ſwete bread a la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be neceſſarely ſhuld be kyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led, whom they eate, the nyght <note place="margin">luke, xxii, Exodi, xii</note> before theyr delyueraunce out of bondage, which being a per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>petual ſygne &amp; token of theyr deliuerau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce was continuallye obſerued among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whych in verye dede was a ſhadowe and fygure of gods mercy &amp; fauou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re toowardes hys creatures, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we were yet his enemies, that lyke as they whych were ſealed wyth the blood of the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be were preſerued from daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous plages y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ouerwhelmed
<pb facs="tcp:4069:18"/> the fyrſt borne of Egipt, &amp; were couerd wyth the mercyful wyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges of god, and ſet theyr fleſhe, whych ſerued in moſt vyle ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitude, or cruel bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dage, vnder the vnbeleuing kyng Pharao, in fredom, wherof to aſſure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he gaue the land of Canaan for theyr habitacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vtterli, therout expelling y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> enemies of his peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, that frely wythout checke, they myght poſſeſſe the promy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed land, that floweth wyth mil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke &amp; hony: Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo that al ſoules which were in the yron cheynes of da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation bondaged to deth, &amp; perpetual darkenes thorowe Adams tranſgreſſion, ſhuld by the meanes of thys annoynted ſauiour, appoynted of god the father before the foundacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the worlde was leyed, be made fre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dampnacion which vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faynedlye
<pb facs="tcp:4069:19"/> truſted in hym. For thys was the ſymple lambe, of whom Eſay the Prophet ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, <note place="margin">Eſay, liii.</note> ſayinge, that he ſhuld not ſtryue for hys fleſſhe. Yea, thee very ſame, that the Euangeliſt hathe appoynted all burdened conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces to go vnto, for a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chardge, ſayinge. <hi>Ecce agnus dei Chriſtus qui tollit peccata mundi.</hi> That is to ſaye. Beholde the <note place="margin">Iohan, i,.</note> la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be of god. Chriſt that taketh awaye the ſynnes of the world. Wherfore that thou mayeſt by thee ſcripture be aſſured that y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> paſſouer lambe eaten at the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liueraunce of theyr bodyes, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a temporall bondage preached the death, and paſſyon of chriſt our lambe, that made hym ſelfe obedient to the mooſt reproche<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full death of the croſſe, by who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe
<pb facs="tcp:4069:19"/> ſtrypes as the Prophete ſaithe we were healed, and alſo the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall delyueraunce of oure ſoules from death, marke well what is wrytten in the ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. <hi>Agni ſtatuuntur in teſtimoniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> veritatis &amp; federis promiſ.</hi> that is <note place="margin">Gene, xxi,</note> to ſaye. Lambes ar appoynted for a wytnes of the truth, &amp; the couenaunt promyſed. And ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore Iohan ſayth. <hi>Agnus occiſus ab origine mundi habet librum fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der is, in quo ſcripta ſunt nomina</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Apoc. xiii.</note> 
               <hi>ſanctorum,</hi> That is to ſay. The lambe that was kylled fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the begynnynge of the world: hath the boke of couenaunt, wherin be wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> names of the ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Nowe to make his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to be more apte to recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue thys myſterie, &amp; to ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr
<pb facs="tcp:4069:20"/> eyes to perceaue the peace offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe promyſed by the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and now come to do the wil of hys father that ſente hym, a la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be to be ſlayne, to appeaſe his wrath, conceyued thorow Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s fal. That, as Adam couered al fleſhe by his diſobedience with damnacion, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo the obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that was in chriſt, ſhulde couer it wyth ſaluacion: He ſayd vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, go ye into the cytye to a certayn man whom ye ſhal me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, and ſay you vnto him. <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter vicit, tempus meum prope eſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Math, 24</note> 
               <hi>apud te facio paſca cum diſcipulis meis,</hi> that is to ſay. The May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſayth, my tyme is at hande, I wyl kepe myne eaſter at thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne houſe with my diſciples. As who ſhuld ſaye, the tyme is co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me that the heauenly wil of my father ſhulde be fulfylled, &amp; by
<pb facs="tcp:4069:20"/> my paſſion wrought for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and conſolation of Adam, &amp; his poſteritie, whos froward<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he diſobeyed hys wyl, plucked hys indignatyon and wrathful vengeaunce vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his head. But now beholde the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable tyme that god my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thorow loue, lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth for an attonemente, &amp; as a louing fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther glad to receyue the ſhepe, that were loſte for ſynne, hathe not ſpared me, his onli begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſonne to throwe me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hys im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>periall trone, into the bottome of the earth, that whoſoeuer be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leueth in me ſhuld haue lyfe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtyng, I am he, promyſed by the prophetes to make thys agrement of whom Eſay ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth. <hi>Ecce virgo concipiet &amp; pari</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſaye. vii</note> 
               <hi>et filium &amp; vocabitur nome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eius Emanuel,</hi> that is to ſay. Behold
<pb facs="tcp:4069:21"/> a byrgyn ſhal conceyue &amp; bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge forthe a ſonne, and hys na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me <note place="margin">Math. i.</note> ſhalbe called Emanuel. And as mathew ſayth. <hi>Qui ſaluum fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciet populum ſuum Iſrael,</hi> that is to ſaye. Whych ſhal make falſe hys people Iſrael. I am the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifice, yea, the onely ſacryfyce that muſt in my bloud waſhe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes iniquitie and dreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and none but I alone. For where the prieſt &amp; leuite hath paſſed by the woun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded man, vnable to helpe him I am come to bynde vp hys wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, yea to make hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hoole, I am the mediator appoynted betwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne god and ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, euen the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus <note place="margin">Timo. 2</note> chriſt, for this purpoſe cho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſen of God my father to heale the ſycke that nede a pheſyſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and preache beliuerau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:4069:21"/> the captiue, wythout me ther is no mediator, for I am come into the world for no other pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe, but to ſaue ſynners. I am that ſpirituall rocke ſente into <note place="margin">i, Corin, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> thys wyldernes, of whom your fathers haue dronke, &amp; ſo muſt you or els ye peryſſhe for thyrſt I am that pure and liuely vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, whos leaues neuer wyther <note place="margin">Iohan, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> nor fal away: whoſo is not pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in me, my father wil plucke him vp by the rootes. I am the <note place="margin">Iohan, vi</note> bread ſent downe from heauen who ſo is replenyſhed wyth me ſhal neuer taſt of death, I am y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iohan, x.</note> dore an ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> entre to my father, vnto whom no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cometh but by me. For he that clymmeth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the walles is as the ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re ſaythe, a thefe or a robber. I onelye do geue lyfe vnto my ſhepe. I am the God of Abraham,
<pb facs="tcp:4069:22"/> Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iſaac and Iacob, euen theyr ſauegarde &amp; mercy ſeate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <note place="margin">Math, xxii,</note> I am he, whych putteth a waye your iniquities euen for myne owne ſake, and beyng the lorde your creator, for loue wyl reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre them no more, for I am the Lord, and wythout me there is no ſauiour, the pathe truly ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue I troden to god my father, <note place="margin">Eſaye, 43</note> that you ſeynge my foote ſtep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes ſhulde at noo tyme erre.</p>
            <p>Thus good brethren, whan he had by preachyng of his death and merites, inſtilled into hys diſciples hartes, vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding that they might perceaue theyr ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and not theyrs alone, but alſo of the hole worlde, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had euen from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynning choſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> witneſſes of hys afflictyons, that after thee thing was fyniſhed which they
<pb facs="tcp:4069:22"/> perſonallye behelde wyth more fyrme &amp; ſtable faith, they might preache this deſyre ſyght &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſurable comforte of al fleſhe among the gentyles and vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuing nacions: He dyd not on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly wyth expreſſe wordes decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re hys goinge into Ieruſalem, hys euel intreature amongeſte the hyghe preſtes, Phariſies &amp; cruel bloud ſuckers, and fynal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly his death, that they hearing theſe wordes myght with more diligens attende to marke the experiens therof: but alſo wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the paſſouer lambe ſhuld be ea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten, whyche as I before ſayde, was the token of theyr delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce out of Egypt, and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fredom of theyr fleſhe, by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che delyueraunce theyr ſoules were not exempted from the ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rannos gulffe of hell, ſynne, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:4069:23"/> death, neyther y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> fathers wrath pacyfied dewe vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>greſſion, but continually han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, mooſt terryblie ouer theyr heades, ſo that they yet were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubiectes yf death, and da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: he therfore to preache vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them a perfect delyueraunce or fredom of both body and ſou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le, to be nomore vnder the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of deathe, but of lyfe and ſaluacion, at this hys laſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, whan the toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this body ly delyueraunce ſhuld be eaten which was but the ſygnificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thys lambe, that was nowe preſent amonge them, by whoſe death al ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kynd ſhuld be low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from vtter darkenes, &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cheable fyer, to ſatiſfie this myſterye, &amp; to make it euydent, he toke bread &amp; after he had ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thankes to God hys father, he brake it, ſaying. Take, eate, <note place="margin">math, 26. Luk. xiiii</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:4069:23"/> this is my bodye whych ſhalbe broken for you, lykewyſe he to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke the cup, ſayinge, thys is my bloud of the new teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſhalbe ſhed for many in the remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theyr ſynnes, For yf the arme of god and hys mygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty power was ſo hyghlye eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> delyueraunce of theyr mortal bodyes, from a mortall tyrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that it vouchſaued him to eſtablyſhe it wyth thys ſyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne or token, for a memoriall of hys grace towardes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, being yet not take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the cheynes of darkenes, than whan ſoeuer the deuyll aſſaulted them cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyuating theyr wyttes with ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſualitie, to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forget the lorde, that the wytnes of his be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nignite ſhulde alwayes accuſe theyr ingratitude, &amp; moue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, how moch more ought this ſigne or ſacramente of the Lordes death to be hyghly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regarded
<pb facs="tcp:4069:24"/> amonges vs Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ans, whych preacheth vnto vs a thyng farre better tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a body<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly deliueraunce, from a bodely tyraunt, namely the delyuerau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce from eternal dampnacion &amp; the kyngdom of darkenes, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whanſoeuer the ramping lyon Sathan ſeketh to deuour our ſoules, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arg vnto ſyn, and deſperacion, we by this ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ar put in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce that our ſauiour Chriſt was the promyſed ſede of the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whych ſhuld breake the ſerpen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes head, whych moued our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to banniſſhe vs from hys ſyght, and hath in hys death, &amp; bloudſheding, ſlayne the leuia than that had power ouer deth Wherfore as the lambe was y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſygne appointed to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue tyl the euerlaſtinge ſauiour, euen Chriſte
<pb facs="tcp:4069:24"/> our la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be came, to preache the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liuerau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of theyr body fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the paynefull ſeruitude, of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giptians: Euen ſo this bread &amp; wyne is the ſacrament, appoin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted by chriſt to preach his moſt precious death, our redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tyl he come to iudge the quicke and y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> dead. And therfore good brethren after the immolacion of Chriſte Ieſus, our paſſouer la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be the Iſraelites ſygne ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, becauſe the innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t lambe in very dede, appoynted of god before the creation of the world (to be ſlayne) was come, whome it ſygnified and hath to aſſure vs of his death, and commyng agayne, left vnto vs bread and wyne, as a ſygne and token to confyrme vs weakelynges in fayth, that he hath died for our ſynnes to pacifye the wrath of
<pb facs="tcp:4069:25"/> hys father, and is ryſen for ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> iuſtification, thee yron bandes of death, braſt in ſonder, and he wyth triumphante victorye, by the power of god, hath penetra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted the cloudes to geue ſaluaci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on. So that the ryghtuouſnes (as Paule ſaythe) that pleaſed <note place="margin">Roma, iii</note> god was the redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that is in chriſte Ieſus, thorough who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the terrible vengeaunce of god is paſſed ouer vs, and wee ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptyon, and that ye ſhuld not doubt, but that God by hym is wonne to be our fren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, marke wel thys his own te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony. <hi>Hic eſt filius meus dilec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus in quo mihi bene co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>placui, ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum audite,</hi> that is to ſay: This <note place="margin">math. iii, marke, ix</note> is my beloued ſonne, in whom I am well pleaſed, heare hym. As the lambe therefore was ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poynted
<pb facs="tcp:4069:25"/> by Moyſes theyr lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der choſen of god, a memoriall or ſygne of goddes goodnes, in that he made them fre men, as touchynge theyr bodyes from pharaos yocke the nyght befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, it came to paſſe: Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo this bread and wyne was aſſigned, a perpetual ſygne by our Moy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes, choſen of god by hys preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bloude to leade vs from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting death, and dampna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion as a ſygne of goddes mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy towardes vs, in that he hath ſent hys only begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus, in the ſhape of ſynfull fleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhe beyng w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſyn, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne ſyn in the fleſhe, &amp; to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quere death for theyr ſake, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of a pure loue truſted in hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> nyghte before his deth, now by this ſig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne bread &amp; wyne, chriſt to inſtru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cte hys Apoſtles whom he had
<pb facs="tcp:4069:26"/> choſen to ſupport ſtedfaſtlie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge the Iewes, the delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of our ſoules fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death exhibited playnely before they eyes, that, that followed, name<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly hys paſſion, and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte of the ſame, ſaying. Take eate, this is my bodye whych ſhalbe geuen for you, do this in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of me. That is to ſaye, euen as ye ſe this bread broken for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of your outward ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and thys wyne dronke for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame, being ſo neceſſary, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wythout it your outward ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> periſheth, for hon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger, and hauing it, the body is defended from ſtaruing. Euen ſo I, myne own ſelf perſonally whom ye ſe, fele &amp; know, beyng the mynyſter of thys whych ye do receaue, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as ſurely as ye behold the brekyng hereof and know
<pb facs="tcp:4069:26"/> kyng hereof, and know that ye haue receyued hit, ſo ſureli ſhal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be crucified, re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for your ſynnes, and in hit ſhal de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerue fre remyſſyon of al youre iniquyties by whoſe merytes, thy vnryghtuous ſoule is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de rightuous, for euer, yf thou forſakeſt ſynne: for this was ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen for the comfort of your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whom god hated for ſynne, for to reconcyle it to thee fathers fauour agayn, &amp; to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death eternal. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore, for aſmoch as by neceſſitie we are enforced dayly to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort our bodye, with bread &amp; drinke Euen ſo are we dayly enforced to comfort our ſoule with the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Teſtamente in Chriſtes bloude, ſo that now wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoeuer our ſperit, beginneth to faynte
<pb facs="tcp:4069:27"/> for ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, that it behoueth vs to breake thys bread, &amp; drynke thys wyne in the remembraun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of chriſtes death and of hys comfortable teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te to feade our ſoule w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>all. <hi>Hoc enim eſt bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere de plenitudine miſericordie ſue</hi> that is to ſay. For this is to drinke of the fulnes of his mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy. And thys opened theyr eyes &amp; confyrmed theyr fayth to per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fection to preache that whyche they afterwarde ſawe come to paſſe, accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g as y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> bread was broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Paul therfore i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtructed by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſperit of god to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d this miſterie, ſayde, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> whych I receaued I deliuer vnto you, o ye Corinthians, The nyght be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore he was betrayed, he toke bread, &amp; brake it, ſaying, this is <note place="margin">1, Cori. 11,</note> my bodye, whych is broken for
<pb facs="tcp:4069:27"/> you, alſo by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> cup he ſayd, thys is y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> new teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in my bloud, as ofte as ye eate of this bread and drinke of this cup ye ſhall preache y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lordes death tyl he co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me: Yf now y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the perſonal bodi of chriſt, fleſhe &amp; bloud had ben ther (as ye dreame) than wolde not paul haue ſaid, ye ſhal prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che the lordes death til he come But rather he wold haue ſayd, behold corinthes, here is chriſt ꝑſonal bodye amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges you, but paule aſſuredly taught by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ghoſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> this was not y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> body, but the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> body, ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore he ſayd, as oft as ye eate &amp; drynke of this bread &amp; wyne, ye ſhal preache his deth, whych is exalted aboue y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> cloudes, tyl he come agayn, for he is departed hens to be oure attorney befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re the trone of Maieſtye of the
<pb facs="tcp:4069:28"/> of the which departure y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture beareth vs wytnes, ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by hys own mouth, ſaying. <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do ad patrem paraturus vobis lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum,</hi> that is to ſaye, I go to my father, to prepare you a place. And agayn. <hi>Veritate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dico, expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit vobis vt abeam, Si non abiero co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolator ille non veniet ad vos, Sin abiero, mitta ad vos,</hi> that is to ſaye, I ſay for truth. It is ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deful that I go hence, yf I goo not hence that comforter ſhall not come vnto you, but yf I go hence, I wil ſend him vnto you Whyche ſperite is not ſente to cloke our wyckednes, or to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fer vs to dwel in darkenes and in errour, but as Iohan ſayth, to reproue the worlde of ſyn, of vnryghtuouſnes and of iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment. <hi>De peccato, quia non credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioh, viii</note> 
               <hi>in me. De iuſtitia, quia ad pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4069:28"/> 
               <hi>vado &amp; poſt hac non videbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis me. De iudicio quia princeps huius mundi iam iudicatus eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is to ſaye. Of ſyn, becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe it beleued not in me. Of iuſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce, becauſe I go to my father, &amp; after thys you ſhall not ſee me. Of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, becauſe the prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of this world is now iudged. And therfore ſayth chriſt I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue manye thynges to tell you, but ye are as yet vnable to bea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re them awaye, But I go vnto my father whych hath ſent me, that according to my promes I may ſend you, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſperit of truth which ſhal without doubte lea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de you into all truthe, to do the wyll of my father. The ſperite receaued Paule whan his eyes were opened, Whyche moued hym to teſtyfye in thys wyſe of our mediator, ſaying. Chriſt is
<pb facs="tcp:4069:29"/> the biſhop of our ſoules, which wyth an oblation of hys owne <note place="margin">Hebre. 10,</note> precious body, hath offered vp hym ſelfe ones for all on the al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tare of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> croſſe, wheron he hath made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perfecte for euer who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath ſanctified, beyng ſoche an hygh byſhoppe whych hath gone thorowe the heauens and ſytteth on the right hand of the trone of Maieſtie, there beyng the admynyſtrator of the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting tabernacle, whom god hath made and not ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Whoſe ſperite hath taught paule thys doctrine, that ſo farre differeth from yours. Did not the ſperit of god, whom chriſte promyſed to lede al his, in al truth? Who taught you then this doctryne that thus rebellethe agaynſte truthe? the contrarye vnto thee truth? Which is a lye of whom
<pb facs="tcp:4069:29"/> the deuyll is father as wytneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the ſcripture. Come hether all ye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that ſo ſtoutlye ſtande in this Lutherian errour, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue (as ye are ſhameles) thee ſperit of truth, which ſpeaketh in Paule. Debate the matter with him. Trye your ſelues, as ye moſt fondely endeuor, to be more wyſer than the ſperite of God, which hath manifeſt ſayd that chriſt ſytteth on the ryght hande of the trone of maieſtie, to be an aduocate for mannes imperfection, you ſaye that his bodye is in the ſacrament, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der forme of breade, fleſſhe and bloud euen as he was borne of the byrgyn Marye: O good brethren hit wolde pytye anye Chriſtian hart to ſee, how with out ſhame ye goo about wythe your deuylyſhe ſophiſtrye and
<pb facs="tcp:4069:30"/> deceauable dreames to dyſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the workes of thee lyuynge god, who hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded hys ſonne to ſytte vpon hys ryght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, according to the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the prophet Dauid, ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge, <hi>Dixit dominꝰ domino meo ſede a dextris meis, donec poſuero inimicos tuos ſcabellum pedum tuorum,</hi> that is to ſay. The lord ſayd vnto my Lorde, ſyt at my ryght hande, vntyl I ſhal ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke thyne enemies thy fote ſtole Alas what meane you thus wil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>linglye to reioyſe in darkenes, ſyns gods word, beyng y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lyght of our feete, hath ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly ſhewed vs that no iote of the law or te<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtymonyes of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ꝓphetes, ſhuld eſcape vndone in chriſt, the end <note place="margin">mathe, v:</note> of the lawe, &amp; prophetes, whoſe mouthes were not open to ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke thinges in vayne, wherfore,
<pb facs="tcp:4069:30"/> ſyns theyr teſtimonies ar true, whych of neceſſytie muſt be ful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fylled by Chriſt, for aſmoch as god had ſo ordeyned hit, howe dare ye agayne ſaye the ſperite of truth, whych affyrmeth hym not only to be ther perſonallye on the right hand of his father, but alſo hathe appoynted hym to come agayn, in the confyrma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of the hole worlde, euen in the ſame, from that he departed to gather the corne into the bar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne, &amp; burne the chaffe wyth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quencheable fyere, and yet ſaye you that he is here in the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, horribly wyth your lyes, blaſphemyng the ſacred Teſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, ſanctifyinge in the bloud of thee lambe, beynge the lawe in dede, whom he hath delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto his people, to directe them in theyr waye to perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:4069:31"/> nomore wrytten in the table of ſtone, but in hys beloued te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple the ſymple hartes of the fayth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full, as he hym ſelfe affyrmeth, ſayinge. I wyl geue my lawes <note place="margin">Hebre, 8</note> in theyr mynde, &amp; in theyr her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes wyl I wryte them, I wylbe theyr god and they ſhall be my people, euen this law vnadvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly as I ſuppoſe, ye deſpyce, and frowardly deny this truth whom the ſperit of truth hathe therin wrytten, beyng ſealed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the precious blood of chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, but it is manyfeſte in thee ſcripture, that he whych diſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Moyſes lawe, dyeth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mercye vnder twoo or thre wytneſſes: Of how moch more ſorer punyſhment (ſuppoſe ye) ſhal he be counted worthy, why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che treadeth vnder fote the ſon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne of god, &amp; counteth the bloud <note place="margin">Hebre, 10.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:4069:31"/> of the newe teſtament (whereby we are ſanctified) and vngodly thing, and doth diſhonour the ſperit of grace. Alas what diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour can ther be more to the moſt hieſt, that of mercy and of faythfulnes hathe ſende vnto vs ſelye wretches his holy ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite to guide the ſtarne of oure ſences y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> at no tyme they ſhuld fal vpon the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous rockes of erroure and falſe doctryne: than lytle regardyng his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyful kindnes, not only to ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke manyfeſte hereſye agaynſte this truth, but alſo mooſt arro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gantly to iudge our weake ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite able to confounde the wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedom of God myniſtered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs by hys bleſſed worde and mooſte ſtoutlye dyſdayne to be ruled thereby<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Coulde a ſhyp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe beynge toſſed hether and
<pb facs="tcp:4069:32"/> hether &amp; thether in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſea, &amp; ready of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> vnmercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full water to be ouerwhelmed, be ſcotfre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> danger, yf y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> rude and vnlerned marynors ſhuld agayn ſay, the wyſdom of theyr pilate vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god hath reue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led the craft &amp; polycye through his gracious ayde to leade her from perels? No truly. Verely nomore is your wyſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> able, in theſe troubelous opynyons or diſceatfull gynnes of Sathan where wyth he purpoſethe to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowe the ſhyppe of youre vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, to rule her dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerles, yf ye agayn ſay the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of your lodeſma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or ſterer, whom God by hys almyghtye power hath inſtructed to leade you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> errour to knowledge, from darkenes to light, &amp; fynal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly from a lye to infallible truth
<pb facs="tcp:4069:32"/> Therfore as the willing mary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors that couet the ſauegarde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhyp (partely for the owner ſake, whom they loue, &amp; chieflye for theyr lyues ſake whych ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vpon the ſhyppe) diligently do marke, and obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly do folow the counſel of theyr pylate, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther adde they, or dymynyſſhe they any iote of his wil, leſt the ſhyppe peryſſhe. Euen ſo good brethren, yf ye loue god whych is the owner of your ſoules, yf they be faythfull, or yf ye haue any reſpect to your own lyues, whych ſtandeth in the fulfyllin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of hys commaundementes, diligently bothe heare and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe gods worde, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the to leade thy vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding into al truth, to whom ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther adde thou or dymynyſſhe any thyng, leſt thy vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:4069:33"/> peryſſhe by errour. For it is wrytten in the ſcripture. Yf any man adde any thing to the worde of prophecye, I wyl ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de vnto him the plages that ar wrytten in thys worde. And yf <note place="margin">apoc. xxii</note> any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal dimynyſh any iote of this word, god ſhal take hys part out of the boke of life and out of the holy cytie. Alas why then runne ye this hedlong in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your own confucion, louing your owne fantacyes ſo well y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ye mooſt vnkyndely vylypend the truth of thys his mooſt ſacred word, whych teacheth vs that Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes natural bodye, accordynge to the prophetual teſtimonye, was crucified, dead, &amp; buryed, and the thyrde daye roſe frome death to lyfe, and aſſended into
<pb facs="tcp:4069:33"/> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther ſytting on the right hand of god his father, and yet contrarye to thys truth: ye ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue added your opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon vnto your owne ſoules, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ye repent, that thys natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral body, whom the holy ghoſt affyrmeth to ſyt on the hand of god, hath tranſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciat it ſelf into bread &amp; wyne. Thus phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantia hath be wytched you in ſoche ſort that ye thynke truth to be a lye, and your abhomina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble lye, truth, but I wyl tel you one thing, which the holy gooſt wold in no cauſe ſhulde be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten. That Chriſte came not to do his own wyl, but the wyl of hys father, whych ſent hym<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But hys fathers wil was that the natural body of chriſt, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che was crucified dead and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed, after hys reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de
<pb facs="tcp:4069:34"/> aſſende into heauen and ſyt on hys ryghthande, therfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re muſt it be graunted (yf your lye ſhuld be the truth, as ye ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe it) that chriſt hath not one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly preuaricate his fathers wil, for that he hathe, (as you ſaye) diſobediently forſaken hys fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſyde, and trone of celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al bleſſe &amp; tranſubſtanciat him ſelfe, beynge of a nature incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptyble, into bread and wyne that ſhal peryſhe, (For the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture ſayth) that all thynge ſene wyth our eye, ſhal conſume, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſhe, &amp; wyther a way, and that nothing is for euer but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word whyche continually preacheth chriſt oure ſauiour, but alſo he hath (as youre truth teſtyfieth of hym) openlye diſſembled in that he ſayd he came to ſatiſfye the wyl of hys father and that
<pb facs="tcp:4069:34"/> he hadde ſente vs the ſperite of truth, and now your truth hath both accuſed him of diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s for tranſubſtanciatinge of hys natural body into bread &amp; wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to hys fathers wyll, and alſo proued the holy ghoſt a lyar, whyche hath teſtified all fleſſhe, that faythfully beleued in the ſonne of god to be ſaued by the obediens of Chriſt Ieſu in whom god almyghtye is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſfied. But ſuppoſe you (good brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) that god can ſuffer his ſonne this to be reported of you of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath ſo wel diſſerued or hys word thus to be ſclaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered which is pure and truth, and that wythout any cohercio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or tellyng you of your fault, no no, iudge not him to be a ſhrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king god, or one that ſetteth pry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce, by youre ſtoute lookes that
<pb facs="tcp:4069:35"/> therby he ſhulde feare any fote at al to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in trial of his truth and tell you of your hereſy: for hys longe ſufferans whych lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth for repentans y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his kynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes myght apere, is not ſo ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der towardes you, that he wyll thus ſee you peryſhe by erroure Whoſe conſpiracie buſylye ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth your da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, all though to you his moſt wicked purpoſe is vnknowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet hath gods mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy eſpyed hit, &amp; reioyſeth not in your deth, wherfore behold the grace y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> it offered vnto you by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> holy gooſt which entendinge to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in trial of goddes truth, by gradacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> refuteth your da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble errour &amp; diſorderi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of gods wil, &amp; proueth y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> natural bodi of chriſt our ſauiour after hys re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſyt on y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> rightha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of god hys father, &amp; for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> proffe of
<pb facs="tcp:4069:35"/> thys matter we call Luke th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee Euangeliſt to wytneſſe, where he wryteth that y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Maries year<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly in the ſabothe daye came, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge to the coſtume to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> body of Chriſt, but wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they came to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> monument, they founde the ſtone rolled a waye, whan they entered to ſe, the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy was away wherw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re maruelouſly aſtoniſhed, but in this ſodayne traunſe &amp; fayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynes of hart, two men in whyt aparel apered vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaying. <hi>Quid queris viuentem in mortuis ſurrexit no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt hic.</hi> That is to ſay Why ſeeke you him that liueth among the dead? He is ryſen, he is not here. And alſo accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them of forgetfulnes, ſayd vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, haue ye forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what he tolde you in Galilie, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> it was expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for the ſon of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to be
<pb facs="tcp:4069:36"/> vnder thee poore of ſynners, to be crucified, and ryſe agayn the thyrd daye, and ſo to enter into glorye, Yea, &amp; becauſe he wold not haue hys dyſcyples vnex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert of thys hys reſurrection &amp; what ſhuld become of this hys body, a litle before his death to reuele vnto them the myſery of his impaſſible body now glori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyed, he toke certayn of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him, and ſayd ſome of you ſhal <note place="margin">math 17, marke. ix Luk. ix.</note> not ſe death, vntyl ye ſe the ſon of man in hys glorie, and forth with vpon the hyl thabor in the preſens of Peter, Iames, &amp; Io<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>han, he tranſfigurated his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural body by the power of his godhead, not as ye dreame into bread and wyne which ſhal pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifie, but into an immortal ſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe, the phiſnamy of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>remay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng, <note place="margin">Apoc. i. Dan, xvii</note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundynge them that
<pb facs="tcp:4069:36"/> it ſhuld be vnknowen, tyl after the teſtymonye of the prophete, were fulfylled whyche ſpake in Chriſte to hys father, ſayinge. Thou haſt taken my ſoule out of hel, and haſt not ſuffered thy ſayncte to ſe corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thys, they were called to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie of Chriſt crucified &amp; prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che euen vpon the howſe toppe the reſurrection of our ſauiour being the fyrſt fruytes of them <note place="margin">i: corin: 15:</note> that ſlepte in hym, of the whych reſurrection Paule ſpeaketh in thys wyſe, ſayinge. <hi>Reſurrexit Chriſtus a mortuis per gloriam pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tris</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Roma, vi</note> 
               <hi>iam non moritur mors illi vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra non dominatur,</hi> that is to ſay Chriſt is ryſen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amonge the deade, through the glory of the father. Now dyeth he not, deth ſhall hence forth haue nomore power ouer hym. Now good
<pb facs="tcp:4069:37"/> brethren ſyns that the ſperite of truth hath aſſuredly taughte, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> the ſame body which was cruci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fied, dead, &amp; is ryſen agayn ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> apoſtels haue wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſed of hym, yf you dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tely atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; awake out of your ſlepe he wyll alſo reueyle vnto you, what bodi this was after his re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; what became therof ſo euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly that except y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; turne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your wycked Imagi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nacion, &amp; all other of your fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the clergye, whych thus ſpurneth agaynſte gods truth, it wil plucke a hoode ouer your heades furred with fearful iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gemente &amp; vnquencheable fyer, Wherfore geue eare vnto thee Euangeliſt whych more playne lyer expreſſeth thys bodye than ye haue cauſe to doubte. After theſe wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had thus talked a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g
<pb facs="tcp:4069:37"/> the diſciples, that at theyr com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng his body was abſent out of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ther aroſe amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſodayne wonderyng how thys myght be, &amp; behold. ii. of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany that thus talked of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, went from Ieruſalem vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyl a certayn vyllage, called E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maus, vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt apered beyng euen the laſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they tal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked of, aſking the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what commu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nication this was, &amp;c, as follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in the text. Reade &amp; iudge In concluſion nyght drewe on, they compelling hym to tarrye wyth them. And it came to paſſe as he ſate at thee table wyth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perſonally he toke bread brake it, and gaue it them, wher vpon they knew hym, and ſo he vaniſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhed away, here note good fren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, that the ſcripture ſpeaketh as yet of no tranſubſtantiation,
<pb facs="tcp:4069:38"/> For the body that brake thys bread was a perſonal bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, hauing fleſſhe and bones; &amp; the ſences of a naturall bodye. As you ſhal manyfeſte percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue hereafter, appoynted wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any alteration to enter into glory. They here vpon callyng to mynde thys ſygne, wherein before his deth he vouchſaued to preache his precious death, the delyueraunce of our ſoules from eternal captiuitie, ſtrayte forth they knewe hym, ſayinge. Dyd not our hartes burne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in vs, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he thus talked wyth vs of the ſcripture. Now good brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe the ſubtyle ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent ſhal not by errour deceaue youre wyttes, to ſurmyce that whych is not, bryngynge vpon your ſelues ſwyfte dampnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it hath to confyrme you in thys
<pb facs="tcp:4069:38"/> truth made playne what bodye thys was, farre otherwyſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye dreame, noo ſoche body that was willing to tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſubſtancy at it ſelfe into a dead thyng, why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che could nether fele, taſt, ſe, go nor ſpeake, in whom ther is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lyfe, nor ſoule, marke ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore how the holy ghoſt hande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth thys matter, by hys holye Euangely on. After theſe twoo me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that were at Emaus, knew hym by the breakyng of bread, they returned vnto Ieruſalem fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe they came, where ther were gathered together of the diſciples aleuen in nomber co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming &amp; talkinge of theyr May<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter chriſte, lately ryſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead and ſeyn of Peter, whoſe talke to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme, theſe two bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to declare what hadde be fallen them in theyr iorney to Emaus
<pb facs="tcp:4069:39"/> as touchinge hys reſurrection. And whyle they thus talked of him, he apered agayne amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaying. Peace be with you: But thei ſomwhat fearful with thys ſtraunge ſyghte, ſuppoſed hym to be ſome ſperit, whom to put oute of doubte, he ſpake in thys wyſe, ſayinge. Why are ye thus troubled or what moueth your hartes thus foundly to I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magyne fantaſyes, be holde my handes, my feate, am I not eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he, that hath caſt your accompt &amp; diſchardged youre det betwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne my father &amp; you, as my ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit at the houre of my moſt byt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter affliction, vttered ſayinge. <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſummatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, &amp;c.</hi> Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter is at iſſue, thy ſaluacion is made perfecte, yf thou abyde in me. Yf you myſtruſte me proue handell me, and ye ſhall no leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:4069:39"/> doo but confeſſe my body far to diſſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſperite, whych hath neyther fleſſhe, and bones as ye ſe me haue, whan he hadde thus deſtorbed hys natural body vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to them to confyrme theyr faith he ſhewed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both feate &amp; han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des: Yet not wythſtanding this manyfeſt demonſtratyon, ſome of them doubted, partly for ioy and partly for the ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſight whom to ſet fre wythout ſuſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he demaunded of them, we ther they had any meat to eate, vnto whom, ſone after hys de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde, they offered parte of a broyled fyſſhe and an honycom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be, and in preſens before theyr eyes he eate it. Thus you ſee that he hadde not onelye fleſhe, bones, and a perſonall bodye, lyke vnto them, but alſo all the ſences of a naturall bodye na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely
<pb facs="tcp:4069:40"/> felyng, ſeyng, hearyng, taſtynge, &amp; goyinge. <hi>Et hec om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia que ſcripta ſunt ad noſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinam</hi> 
               <note place="margin">fo, 15,</note> 
               <hi>ſcripta ſunt vt per patienti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>am ſcripturarum ſpem habeamus</hi> that is to ſay, Al theſe thynges that are wrytten, are wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for our learnyng, that through the pacience of thee ſcriptures, we ſhulde haue hope. Whyche al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye wylbe of force ſtronge y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to confute thys errour, whych by enchauntement wold haue ther a phantaſtical body, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> is a bodye by coniecture who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye ſaye, can nether be felt wyth hand neyther ſeyn with eyes of the body, but only wyth y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> eyes of your faythe. O good brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> how longe wyl ye play the part of Iamnes and Iambres whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che wyth mooſt diſceatful ſorce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye haue reſyſted the wil of god
<pb facs="tcp:4069:40"/> thynke you that the wrathfull vengeaunce of god, whych fell vpon them, can myſſe you play<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge the ſame part, no truly, for agaynſt ſoch thar ſtouburnely wythſtande the truth wythout repentaunce, god ſharpeth his ſworde and bendeth his lawe, &amp; ſhal loke narowly w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hys eyes, that he myſſe not hys marke, but that he may hit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ryght for I am ſure that ye ar not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunt, How that moyſes rod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de <note place="margin">Pſal, viii</note> hath deuoured theyr feyned ſerpent and that dangerles, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo ſhal truth vaunquiſhe your errour and conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pne your fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in that ye loue youre wyttes ſo wel, that ſhameles ye wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande the glorious goſpel and ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly accuſe truth of a lie, hath not Chriſt euen wyth his owne mouth, lynyally deſcrybed hys
<pb facs="tcp:4069:41"/> body to be fleſhe &amp; bloud, &amp; alſo to poſſeſſe al the ſences of a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural body &amp; that to the eyes of hys diſciples, yet contrarye to thys truth, ſay you, that his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is in forme of bread, whyche is dead, and vade of ſences, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo he ſhewed hym ſelfe after his reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſhape &amp; ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and yet agaynſt hys own wyl, ye wyl compel hym to tranſubſtanciat him ſelf, into a new ſhape, brynging a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with all hys me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers into the ſtrayte roume of a pece of bread, or ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ging cake (as ye better allow it) Iudge you now how your So<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phiſtrie, and the ſperite of truth agreeth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But with your pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſuffer me, (I pray you) to reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyth your fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tacye, that ye may perceaue the buylding of youre opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnable to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in trial w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4069:41"/> the ſcripture becauſe it lacketh a groundfyll. Anſwere me ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Luther &amp; your adherentes, wold ye that Chriſtes naturall body, borne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vyrgyn Mary very fleſhe &amp; bloud ſhuld be tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſubſtanciate into thys bread or no? yf ye ſo wold, manifeſt vnto me, I pray you the tyme of this alteracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for aſmoch as nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g can be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of time. Yf ye ſaye it was done at thys his laſte ſupper, whan he inſtituted thys ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by this text. <hi>Hoc eſt corpus meum, quod pro vobis tradituru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> That is to ſay. This is my body which ſhalbe geuen for you. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſcripture blan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth you, for it teachethe vs y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> the natural body of Chriſt whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che brake this bread, afterward to be ſlain vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> croſſe, &amp; buried Agayn, if ye affirme this altera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his bodi to haue cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter his
<pb facs="tcp:4069:42"/> reſurrection, than the ſcripture replyeth agayn geuinge you a fayre checkmate, ſayinge, that after he was ryſen, he bracke bread amongeſte hys apoſtels, in the forme of the crucified bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy, hauing nothyng thereof al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tered, ſauing that nowe it was immortall nomore ſubdued to our carnall paſſyons. Then to conclude yf neyther before hys death, nor after his reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he entered into thys bread, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is youre Imaginacion falſe, But now paraduenture ye wyl demaunde of me, whyche haue diſproued thys magicall tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtanciation, What became of this body thus ryſen, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture maketh you thys anſwere After he hath continued in the yearth. xl. dayes whan he was ryſen, the diſciples, but then ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thered
<pb facs="tcp:4069:42"/> together at Ieruſalem, abyding as they were appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coming of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> promiſed co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, aſſone as he had repeted vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable ꝓmyſe of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſodeynly, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in theyr ſyght he entered into hys glorye, a cloud taking hym out of theyr eyes. And whyle they yet ſtode wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dering at the migh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty arme, and incomprehenſible power of god: to take from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all occaſyons of doubtynge or ſuppoſal what ſhuld folowe of Chriſt thus take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr eyes Beholde an angel apered vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, inſtructi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g theyr ſperit with this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaying, Ye me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of galilie, why ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ye here gaſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, the ſame chriſt which is nowta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhal in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſame ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner apere agayn, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore what is he y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> dare boldelye
<pb facs="tcp:4069:43"/> vſurpe the name of a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; hateth to be reformed by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> holy gooſt, whom god hath left vnto vs to inſtructe vs in Chriſt, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we heare ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> his body is not onely in glorye w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>he his father, in the euerlaſting king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, exempt from trouble &amp; my<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſery, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reygneth nothinge but ryghtuouſnes &amp; peace, whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re it ſhall reygne in power and glory vntyl he hath brought all hys enemies into ſubiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ſtouburnly vpon a froward ſpyte, wyth holde hys truthe in vnrightuouſnes, but alſo accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to the ſcripture ſhall come agayne, to iudge the quycke, &amp; the dead, as dayly we lay in our crede, of whom y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> prophet dauid thus ſpeaketh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Deus manifeſte ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niet deus noſter &amp; non ſilebit, Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisin conſpectu eius exaudeſtet &amp;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4069:43"/> 
               <hi>in circuitu eius tempeſtas valida quia deus iudex eſt.</hi> That is to ſay <note place="margin">Pſal. 49<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> The god that is oure god, ſhal come openly, and ſhall not kepe ſylence. In his ſyght ſhal fyere conſume, &amp; rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d about him ſhal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be a myghty te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſt: becauſe god is a iudge. And Paule ſayth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in this wyſe teſtifying of hys coming. <hi>Ipſe dominꝰ cum hortatu &amp; voce archangeli, ac turba dei, deſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cendet</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Math, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Iohan. 5 Theſſa: 4 2: Theſ: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>de celo &amp; mortui in Chriſto reſurge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c.</hi> That is to ſay. The lord him ſelf ſhal deſcend from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in the encoraging &amp; voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of an Archangell, &amp; wyth the trumpe of God, and the dead in Chriſt ſhal ryſe. &amp;c. And thys co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myng was alſo reueled vnto da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niel the prophete in a vyſion by nyght where he ſawe one like to the ſon of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> comyng out of the
<pb facs="tcp:4069:44"/> cloudes, vnto whom the aged man gaue power and dignitie regall, that all people, trybes &amp; <note place="margin">Dani. vii apoca, i. Philip, ii</note> tonges ſhuld ſerue hym, whoſe power is an euerlaſting power which ſhal neuer be put down, and hys kyndgom endureth in corrupt. Becauſe therfore that we ſhuld aſſuredlye pronounce hym to be the ende of the lawe, and of the Prophetes, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge teſtified in them ſhulde be lefte vndone, but fulfylled by him, to aſſure vs that he wol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de come, that we myght at no ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me be careles, and vnprouyded as were the foolyſſhe vyrgyns, and ſo thorowe oure negligens be ſhutte oute, he gaue vs cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne ſygnes, and tokens that <note place="margin">Ioel, xxxii Math, 24 Ierem 25, Eſay, xiii marke, 13, luke. 21,</note> ſhulde come to paſſe, before the daye of hys commyng euydent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly teſtifyed by thee prophetes &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:4069:44"/> the Euangeliſt as the alteraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſonne and moone, and the decaye of the bryghtnes of the ſtarres wyth ſoch lyke, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny teſtified in the Scriptures: For lyke as the lyghtening go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth from the Eaſt, and ſhyneth <note place="margin">math, 24</note> into the Weſt, ſo ſhall the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge of thee ſonne of man be, and wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be cometh, he wyl not tarrie. <hi>Que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aduentum (vt re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fert Paulus) narret te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poribus ſuis beatus &amp; ſolus potens Rex regu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Timo.</note> 
               <hi>dominus dominantiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, qui ſolus ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bet immortalitatem &amp; lucem habi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tat in acceſſibile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nullus videt.</hi> That is to ſay, Whych coming (as Paule declareth) the kyng of kynges, &amp; Lordes of rulers, who onely hath immortalitie &amp; dwelleth in lyght, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> noman can come to, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> noma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeeth. Paul therfore ſeynge the imperfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:4069:45"/> of our fleſh, which is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to fea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> luſt of our corrupt afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, exhorteth to loke diligentli for his coming of our ſauioure ſaying<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Conuarſatio veſtra erit in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Celo</note> 
               <hi>celis vnde faluatorem aduenturum ſpectatis.</hi> That is to ſay. Youre conuerſation therfore ſhalbe in heauen, whence ye loke for a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour to come, If he be to come, he is not yet come, for whan he cometh he wyl not tarrye, Yf he be not yet come, he is not here, Yf he be not here, than it folow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> his body is not reallye in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Now good brethren ye haue hero y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> doctrine of gods ſperit, what it hath taught of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> natural body of chriſt Ieſu, how it was not only crucified dead &amp; buried, &amp; roſe agayn y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>. iii. day, but alſo that ye ſhulde fantaſye nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of thys body wyth your
<pb facs="tcp:4069:45"/> grooſe carnalitie it hath expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uelye ſhewed, what bodye thys was, wether it we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, where it is &amp; from whens it ſhal come, for as moch therfore as this is y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſperit of truth, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſt at his depar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture promyſed to hys faythfull folowers as a gouernour to lea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de them into al truth, we y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> couet to be called Chriſtians, muſt of neceſſite beleue it, yf wyth chriſt we do entend, to haue any ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, for who ſo beleueth not this his ſoule ſhal not proſper, but y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
               <note place="margin">a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Gal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3 Roma. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> iuſt ſhall lyue by fayth. Chriſte therfore thus ſpeaketh in Ioha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Verely, verely I ſaye vnto you, whoſo heareth my word &amp; bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth him that ſene me, hath euer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laſting life, and cometh not into damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but is paſſed thorow deth vnto lyfe. Iudge you now
<pb facs="tcp:4069:46"/> what ſhal beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of thoſe whych diſpyce, and beleaueth not this truth. Now as touchinge Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers errour, yf that vnder the forme of bread the natural bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of chriſt ſhuld be, it apereth hys ciuilitie to be very ſlender for as moch as he hath ſo vnre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerentlye handeled thys bodye not according vnto hys worthi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, but vnkyndly robbed hym of hys honour whych is his, as natiuelye, as the bryghtenes is the ſon, and as daungerous to be diſceuered, <hi>Quia ipſe eſt glorie</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hebre, i</note> 
               <hi>ſple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dor &amp; figura ſubſtancia patris,</hi> That is to ſaye. For he is thee bryghtnes of the glory, and the Image of the fathers ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce What is he therfore that wyll ſay Chriſtes body to be inglori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous lyns he is the brightnes of his fathers glorie, for in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture
<pb facs="tcp:4069:46"/> it is called y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> glorious day ſtarre, and therfore Peter kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing aſſuredly, glory to belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge vnto thys body ſayd. <hi>Gloria</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſto, nunc &amp; in die<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eternitatis.</hi> That is to ſaye, Glorye be to Chriſt, now and euer. Agayne Iohan not entending to wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe any thynge fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thys bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſayd. <hi>Gloriam honorem &amp; vir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tutem dignus es accipere inſecula,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">apoca. 4.</note> 
               <hi>ſeculoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> That is to ſay, Thou art worthy to haue glorye, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure, &amp; power for euer. Chriſt alſo hath ſayd by the mouth of hys Euangelyſte, that who ſo honoureth not the ſonne, the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me honourethe not thee father, for thys cauſe verely hath god geuen al iudgement to hys ſon <note place="margin">mathe, 11 luke. 10, Iohan. 5.</note> that all men might honour the ſon, euen as they honoured the father. Syns then y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ye dreame
<pb facs="tcp:4069:47"/> chriſtes natural body to be here preſently <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, why ſhal we not then fall down, and worſhyp it. For yf at the name of Ieſus al knyes ſhal bowe (as ſayth the ſcripture) both in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and in yearth, how moch mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re ought they to bowe, yf they ſe hys body (as ye ſay) in the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment. for thys we ſe euen amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs mortal creatures dayly in ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perience, that whan the name of a prynce or emperour in any ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile matters apperteyning to a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> weale is named amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g his ſubiectes, they al vncouet theyr heades: But whan the perſon or body of the kyng is preſente, they fall down vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr knies and honoure him? Howe moche more oughte we, yf it were true as ye ſaye, Whych as is a very lye in dede, to fall downe &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe
<pb facs="tcp:4069:47"/> the euerlaſting prynce &amp; immortal body of Chriſt Ieſus But Luther hym ſelfe hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid the worſhippyng of this bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy, ergo, he muſt of force eyther deny the bodely preſens of chriſt not to be in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or elles robbed the bodye of hys nature and diſhonour the ſperit of gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce, for glorye doth wyllingly fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe thys ſymple and innocent body of Chriſt, becauſe he hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled hym ſelf to death, for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uegarde of hys, as it becometh a good ſhepeherd, wherof y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath thus teſtified ſaying <hi>Gloria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> precedet humilitas.</hi> That <note place="margin">Proue-15</note> is to ſaye, Humilitie goeth befo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re glyrye, Towhom ſubſcribeth the prophet in thys wyſe ſaying <hi>Gloria dominum magna eſt, quia</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſa, xviii Prou-15-</note> 
               <hi>excelſus dominus.</hi> That is to ſaye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Thee glorye of the Lorde,
<pb facs="tcp:4069:48"/> is great, becauſe he is high<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For hys body now is a glorified bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy, reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to be worſhypped of Chriſtians. Therfore to con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clude, it were very abſurde and out of frame to ſaye, that there is his bodi, and deny him that, that his body hath deſerued of vs vnto whom belongeth thee kyngdom, power and glory for euer, and euer. Amen. Agayne Luther wold haue the letter to be ſymplye vnderſtande, wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any interpretacion or troo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe, that becauſe Chriſte ſayde. <hi>Hoceſt corpus meum,</hi> That is to ſay. Thys is my body. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore it is hys body. Surely yf the wyl of God had refuced the interpretacion of hys worde: than was he moch to blame to ſend hys hooly ſperit to myny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſoch gyftes vnto men. But
<pb facs="tcp:4069:48"/> who is he that accuſeth the ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ieſtie of god, or reproueth hym in hys doyinges, therfore they are not al fautleſſe that repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the interpretacion whych agreeth wyth the wyll of God, For yf ye ſtand vpon thys na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe ebbe, that otherwyſe than the letter, there ſhulde be no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretacion, ye ſhuld not only accuſe chriſt him ſelf, whych to hys diſcyples myſtically ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king many thinges very hard, for them to vnderſtande accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> letter, to make it playn vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dyuerſe times and oft expounded vnto them: But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſperit of truthe, for we rede that where as Mathew &amp; Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke the Euangeliſtes haue wryt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten of thys Sacrament in this wyſe. Drynke hereof al, thys is my bloud of the newe teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,
<pb facs="tcp:4069:49"/> Luke and Paule are ſo bold by the ſame ſperit to enterpret and make playner the ſame wordes ſaying, this is the new teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in my bloude, not that the ſenſe differeth, but too interpret thee wordes more playner, to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> fleſhe &amp; bloud which alwayes not led by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſperyt of God, by falſe iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is a ſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bling ſtock to hir ſelf. If thou by the ſame ſperyt hath manifeſtly declared the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me body, beyng now in glorye wyth hys eternal father, not to he in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but hathe by hys choſen myniſter paul, inter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preted the wordes of the eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſtes ſaying, as ofte as ye eate of thys bread &amp; drynke of thys cup, preache ye y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lordes death, tyl he come, why rebelleth Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther &amp; hys adhere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wil of god, or why preferre they theyr Imaginacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, before the
<pb facs="tcp:4069:49"/> the purpoſe of our heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, ſeyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he vnſealed Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les lippes, for this cauſe to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che this ſayinge, vnto the rude corinthia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> therby thei might vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, for what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this viſible ſigne bread &amp; wyne, was inſtituted of chriſt our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, namelye to preache thys inuiſyble grace y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> the breaking of Chriſtes body &amp; ſhedinge of hys precious bloud, hath paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> vengeance of hys father which was deuiſed agaynſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <note place="margin">Iohan. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> &amp; his of ſpryng, &amp; cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſynnes, ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> aſſured affiance w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out waueri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g are planted in thys hys bodye, <note place="margin">Rom, viii</note> ther remayneth no da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for he came to ſeke, and ſaue that was loſte, that all that beleued <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uke. ix.</note> in him, ſhuld haue lyfe euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge, accordynge to the teſty <note place="margin">Iohan. 3.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:4069:50"/> to the teſtymony of the prophet Oſeas. Thy dampnation o Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, came of thi ſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but thy ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uacion of our lord Ieſus chriſt Yf the letter, good brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de be ſymple vnderſtand. Alas what ſhuld our carnal wyſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and dulle ſences, make of chriſt our mercy ſeate and lyuing ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour whych dayly noryſſheth vs wyth hys aboundant grace hath he not called hym ſelfe in the letter, a dore, a vyne and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye wyth ſoche lyke phraſes, in the ſcripture, ye truly I pray the the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good congregation, An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwere me, Wherfore hathe he thus called hym ſelf. Becauſe thou ſhuldeſt iudge him a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial dore, a vyne or waye? no truelye, wherfore than? doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe <note place="margin">Oſee. 14:</note> becauſe thy mortal eye per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceaueth that the propertie of a
<pb facs="tcp:4069:50"/> dore is to ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the waye into the manſyon place, &amp; wythoute the dore noma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can enter dangerles Euen ſo it vouchſaued Chriſte by hys holy ſperit to inſtructe the immortall eye of thy ſoule, namely thy fayth, that chriſt is the onelye dore that leadeth vs vnto god his father, wyth who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as many as beleueth in hys on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſonne ſhal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifye the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ſabaoth of endles ioy, for he alone hathe made thys entre by whom al chriſtians muſt en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, and who ſo clymmeth ouer the walles, and goeth not tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the dore, ſurely he is a the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe and a robber, and as a thefe or robber, for his tranſgreſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſubiect vnto iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo ſhal that ſoule be enda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gered in iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that ſeaketh in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny otherway to god the father
<pb facs="tcp:4069:51"/> that chriſt Ieſus, for by him we haue knowledge of god, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out hym we ſhall neuer knowe god, veryly thus hath he ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with hys owne mouth. Yf any man knoweth me, the ſame kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth him that ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me, wherfore as the dore is the entery to the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſion place. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo Chriſte is our dore to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> father, agayn: as thou dayly by experience ſeeſte the branches of the vyne which taketh mooſture of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> body out of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they iſſue neuer to dye, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually according to his nature, growe grene, &amp; floryſhe bryngyng forth y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> frute of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> vy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne. Euen ſo as many as ar vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faynedly graffed in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> precious body of chriſt our ſauiour ſhall neuer taſte of death, but perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuallye by hys aboundant gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce growe and floryſſhe in vertu
<pb facs="tcp:4069:51"/> and brynge forth frute in hym, agreing to his nature, that is, the denyinge of vngodlynes &amp; doinge good, as y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> prophet wry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth, <hi>Declina a malo &amp; fac bonum</hi> That is to ſaye. Declyne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyl, and do good. Laſt of al, as the way leadeth the pylgryme or wayfaring ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his iorneys ende that he may ther reſt from werines: ſo doth this our aduo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cate &amp; mediator chriſt Ieſu lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de vs which here ar but pylgry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes in this ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge lande com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed aboute wythe all myſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes and deathe to oure owne countrie whom he hath purcha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed, for his faythful flocke with hys holy and ſantyfyed bodye, offered ones for al, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon of our ſynnes, which coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trie endureth for euer exe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all trouble, wherein reynethe
<pb facs="tcp:4069:52"/> the peace of god for euer. wher we ſhal enioy the fruyte of our laboure, and atteyne the goole whereat al the faythful eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the begynning that hath bene, are, and ſhalbe to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fyrma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the whole world hathe wyllingly directed thee courſe of theyr lyfe, namely lyfe euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, the port of chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueyle wythoute werynes tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe Chriſt our lorde as ſaithe the euangeliſt Iohan. <hi>Hec ſcrip ſi vobis qui creditis in nomine fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lii</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iohan, v,</note> 
               <hi>dei, vt ſciatis, quod vitam habe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tis eterna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> That is to ſay. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe thynges haue I wrytten vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to you that beleue in the name of the ſon of god: that ye maye know that ye haue euerlaſting lyfe. Now to conclude chriſt is not a material dore, way, or vy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne but hath in hym y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> qualities
<pb facs="tcp:4069:52"/> of theſe vicible thinges, &amp; thus it pleaſed his mooſte glorious Maieſtie to enforme vs in the knowledge of the vertue of his moſt precious body by thys vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyble ſygnes to augment oure hope to ſaluacion. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo hath he done in thys hys ſacrament ſayinge. <hi>Hoc eſt corpus meum,</hi> That is to ſay. Thys is my bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy, not that hyt is his perſonal body, nomore tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hit is a dore or vyne, but as he hath y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytye of a dore or vyne, ſo lyke caſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath he y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> propertie of thys bread, for bread by nature no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth the body, ſo chriſt by na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture noryſheth y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſoule. Yf ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the letter ſhuld be ſymplye vnderſtande without interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion, how moch ſhulde it ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre the ſperit of god, whyche teacheth vs that Chriſt is our
<pb facs="tcp:4069:53"/> euerlaſting prieſt, according to the order of melchiſedeck, with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out begynning, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out end Al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pha, &amp; Omega, yea how moche ſhuld it make faynt oure hope to beleue y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> incorruptible bodie of chriſt our ſauiour to be tran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciat into a maſſie peace, of bread w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out lyfe or ſoule and made of corruptible elementes But here may you ſe good bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren as it were in a myrror or glaſſe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> grooſe capacitie of our indocible iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of froward fleſhe which ſeketh not hartely to be inſtructed in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> truth or ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uour of the light, but rather to be wyſe in hys own co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyt and worder at the wyſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god, na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mely y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> truth of hys word. As y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> malicious pharaces or ſtubbor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne Iewes amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues won<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dred at y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable wordes of chriſt, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>he ſaid his fleſh was
<pb facs="tcp:4069:53"/> meate &amp; his bloud drinke &amp; that it gaue lyfe euerlaſting, grooſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dering the letter &amp; not the ſpiritual ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of chriſt, ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to preach remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theyr ſyns by the offering vp of his preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous body, wherby y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nous workes of cruel ſatha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were low<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed &amp; hel ſyn &amp; deth clerely van<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quiſhed: ſayd how ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thys man geue his fleſhe to eat &amp; his blou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de to drinke ſuppoſing as Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther &amp; his adherentes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr teth ſhuld eate the fleſh of chriſte, &amp; drinke hys bloud eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it only meate to feade the bely w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>al, but chriſt to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pne theyr fonde ſuſpicion &amp; to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke playne his meaning as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the eati<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of his precious body being y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> foread ſent down from heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to geue lyfe vnto al the worlde, ſayd. <hi>Spiritus eſt qui</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4069:54"/> 
               <hi>qui viuificat, caro no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prodeſt quic quam verba que loquor ſpiritus &amp; vita ſunt.</hi> That is to ſaye. It is <note place="margin">Iohan. vi</note> the ſperite that quickeneth, the fleſhe profyteth nothinge. The wordes that I ſpeke vnto you are ſperyt &amp; lyfe. As who ſhuld ſay it is a ſpiritual matter that I ſpeake of, nothyng appertey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning vnto the fleſhe, for the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite of god of nature endeuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to inſtructe the ſelye poore and faynt ſperyte of man, to be apt to comprehende the wyl of hys creator, for thys ſperyt fea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth the ſoule, and maketh the hart of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ioyful, and therfore maye it very well be aſſembled vnto thys worde meate, for as an hungrye ſtomack beyng by longe faſtynge febled in ſtrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth &amp; out of corage, reioyſeth whan it is ſatiſfied with meate
<pb facs="tcp:4069:54"/> Euen ſo the harte, and ſoule of man, beyng long febled wyth y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wrathfull diſpleaſure of God, vnto whom it was ſubiecte by diſobedience: after the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant mercy of Chriſt frely offe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red hir ſelfe, to appeaſe thys wrathful indignacion, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was noryſhed, it ioyfully lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vp, &amp; prayſed hys ſauiour. And therfore it is a ſpyrytuall meate whych I ſpeake of, geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> only of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſperit, whych feadeth nothing but ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes mind. And thus anſwered he the errour of the Iewes, whyche vnderſtode hym to ſpeake of hys perſonall bodi, becauſe we ſhuld not drea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me, as Luther hathe done any thyng of thys corporal preſens to be in the ſacrament. But in thys opynyon, Luther, &amp; you all whych mooſt vnaduyſedlye
<pb facs="tcp:4069:55"/> haue ſubſcrybed vnto hys er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, haue with your carnal wi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſedom exceded the policie of the wicked worldlinges, which put chriſt to deth. For yf thei eyther by power or ꝓſuacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> could haue the multitude or comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſort of people beleue y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> his bodi had be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in form of bread they wold neuer haue brybed y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> knyghtes of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſepulture w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney, to ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his body was ſtole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> awaye by hys diſcyples in thee night: but bicauſe they were vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>able to proue hys body to be in theyr poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: therfore they fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> largition to bleare the peoples eyes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they myght ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſe but ſtyl ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in vnbeliefe. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo you with might &amp; mayn haue endeuoured to ſaue theyr eyes from the lighte of goddes worde, leſte paraduenture they
<pb facs="tcp:4069:55"/> myght happely ſee &amp; conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pne your hereſy &amp; for this ye thinke it no ſhame to ſet thys deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble errour as a curtayn betwen the peoples eyes, &amp; the ſpiritual eating of this bodye, wherfore vnderſtand you al that labour of this phreneſy ſo that ye waxe wroth with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſperit of the moſte hyeſt, for ſpeakinge truthe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand I ſay, what is meante by the eating of this ſpirituall bodye, verely not thee tearynge wythe the teth, nor dyſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bring of Chriſtes body, but only that we ſhulde aſſuredlye truſt that by hys owne bloude he entered ones for all into the holy place &amp; hath found eternal rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption &amp; alſo being perfect, became the cauſe of euerlaſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that obeye him by the
<pb facs="tcp:4069:56"/> ſacrifice of hys precious bloud thorow the ſperite offered with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out ſpot, vnto god, he hath ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen remiſſyon of al our ſynnes yf we repent, hatyng vngodly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, &amp; holy truſt vnto this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of our ſoule, ſure &amp; ſted faſt by hoope whyche leadeth vs to take thys holde, that where as our vnperfecte fleſhe was vna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble to do or ſatyſfie the wyll of god the father, he hathe by hys precious death &amp; croſſe, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fulfylled the wyl of god, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed hys wrath, and become lyfe euerlaſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that truſt in hym, but alſo is become the entrye of the eternal kyngdom of endles tranquillitie, the pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce dayly receaued of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ar ſantified in him, for here on ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth the lawe &amp; thee prophetes, Wherfore wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoeuer ye brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke
<pb facs="tcp:4069:56"/> thys bread &amp; eate it, wherwyth ye aſſure your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciens y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> being turned into your ſubſtaunce, it noryſheth your bodye, ſo at the breaking hereof ye muſt aſſure your conſcience, that yf ye for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake ſynne &amp; vnfaynedly beleue that thee breakynge of hys bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy hath pourged away our ſyn by the whych we haue poſſeſſed all the merytes of his precious bodye, namely remyſſyon of al our ſynnes and life euerlaſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, He is turned into the immortal incorruptyble and impaſſyble ſubſtaunce of ſoche a faythfull ſoule and wythout dout conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually noryſheth it. <hi>Quicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> er<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>go pane<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hunc co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mederit &amp; ex no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uo teſtamento in ſanguine ſuo ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tificatio, hoc exhanſerit, morte no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> morietur ſed viuent in aeternum,</hi> That is to ſaye. Who ſoeuer
<pb facs="tcp:4069:57"/> therfore ſhal eate thys bread, &amp; ſhal drynke of thys newe teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſanctifyed in hys bloud: y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſame ſhal not dye the death but ſhal lyue for euer. For whan he ſayth whoſo eateth my fleſſhe &amp; drinke my bloud hath life euer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laſting. And whoſo beleueth in me hath lyfe euerlaſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. What dullard is ther that perteyneth not the eatyng of thys bodye, &amp; fayth in hys bloud ſhedi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to be both one, except he wold mooſt wickedly appoynt vs. ii. wayes vnto ſaluacyon one by eatyng of the Sacramente, another by fayth, but yf by eatynge alone the dyſcyples ſhulde haue had lyfe euerlaſting, aſſone as they hadde receaued thys body at y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſupper, what hadde the croſſe and death of Chriſte auayled, But god forbyd that the myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:4069:57"/> of godly men ſhuld at any tyme be entankeled wyth ſoche ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge lerninge &amp; comberous doctryne: which I feare me wol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de ſone come to paſſe, yf y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of our redemer ſhulde car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally according to the letter be vnderſtand, but Chriſt calleth hym ſelfe both helth &amp; lyfe to al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that truſt in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſummate ſacrifice of hys body ones offe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red for al ſynne &amp; vnto them wil <note place="margin">Hebre. ix</note> apeare agayn without ſyn vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſaluation ſendinge vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by hys bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tuous grace y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only &amp; moſt beautiful ambacetor of peace, the importible crowne of euerlaſting glory which with a ſure hope dylygentely loke for the aperaunce of hys moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryous face, Who wil drawe vs w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him to the immutable kyng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hys father wyth who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhal with ioye inexplicable liue
<pb facs="tcp:4069:58"/> eternally, for he hath ſayd thys worde, whyche retourneth not vnto hym emptye. <hi>Vbi ego ſum ibi erit miniſter meus</hi> That is to ſaye. Where I am, there ſhall my myniſter be, for he enioyeth glory, and lyueth for euer, and ſo ſhall we do that truſt in hym for thys is the wyl of God, As Iohan ſayth. <hi>Vt qui vidit filium et credit în eum habeat vitam ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternam &amp; Chriſtes reſuſcitabit eu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in nouiſſimo die.</hi> That is to ſay That he that ſeeth the ſonne &amp; beleueth in hym, maye haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall lyfe, and chriſt ſhal ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe hym in the laſt day, Chriſtes fleſſhe therfore, that it was deli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uered vnto death for oure fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, is called the meat of oure ſoule &amp; hys bloud, foraſmoche as it was ſhedde vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe is called therfore thee dryncke
<pb facs="tcp:4069:58"/> moſt helthful and neceſſarie of our ſoule, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſoule could not haue bene ſaued, but in this doctryne of the ſperit of truth is fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d no tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on into bread nor wyne, nether yet a perſonal body, therfore ye muſt nedes gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t al though it be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt your wylles y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your Imaginacion cometh of your ſelues, and not of god, therfore it muſt be vntrue. <hi>Na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s homo mendax, deus verus eſt in cuius la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>biis nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inventus erat dolus.</hi> That is to ſay. For euery man is a lyar, but God is true, in whoſe lippes was neuer found deceit. Good brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yet ones a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gayn pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſuffer me to aſke you a litle queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> knowlege of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by no meanes hinder you, ꝓffer you it may, to diſcer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne your grief &amp; be healed by the
<pb facs="tcp:4069:59"/> goſpel, Haue ye forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> how y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our ſauiour chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte in his perigrinacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> erth to certify his faithful diſciples of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wil of his father &amp; of his fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uour towardes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had ſent y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ꝓmiſed ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wold receaue hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; beleue i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his name, left, if. ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes to prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che his <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>cious deth y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lauacre of our ſoules, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alone we we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re purged fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſyns, nameli bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyme, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his body, for this caſe only y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> we alwayes ſhuld haue before our eyes and firmely print in our hartes his deth &amp; paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by whom we were ſealed into rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption noo more vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> law whych offered vnto our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s for tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>greſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nothing but da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnatyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but vnder libertie &amp; grace, leſte paradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ping lyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che buſeli ſeketh our deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:4069:59"/> ſhuld at any tyme, ſnatche this chriſt out of our reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce (as he is alwaies redi) by ſon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dry inchynes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he leyeth to ſna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re oure myndes wherebye they myghte forget theyr ſaluacion, therfore of, ii. neceſſarie thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges he made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue in this our mortal lyfe, ſoch neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie vſe, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we cannot ſuſteyne our mortal bodies na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meli water &amp; bread, whereby he ſhewed vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as oft as we ſough<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te by this outward thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fort our body to maynteyn life &amp; y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> vital ſperites therof, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we ought by ſeing of this to pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che vnto our ſoules y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious deth &amp; paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of chriſt our ſauiour which ſuſteyneth, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinualli cauſeth it to ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue, Wherfore for aſmoch as he before his deth iſtituted thes, ii ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, I dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of you whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che
<pb facs="tcp:4069:60"/> of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke moſt honorable or meteſt to be preferred before thother paraduenture ye wold ſaye, the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the bodye is mooſt hieſt to be eſtemed, but yf ye ſtand to that, ye ar lyke to haue a ſodayn fall, for the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture affyrmeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be equall in this wiſe ſaying, theyr endes are one, and the promes annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto them bothe, is one and therfore the ſacramentes ar of equall forſe, that they ar of one ſtrenght the ſcripture proueth in thys wyſe, ſaying, <hi>Quicun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> credit &amp; baptizatus fuerit ſaluus erit.</hi> That is to ſaye, He that be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leued and ſhalbe baptiſed: ſhal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be <note place="margin">Iohan. 6</note> ſafe. Agayn <hi>Qui manducaue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rit carnem meam &amp; bibit meum ſanguinem habebit vitam eterna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> That is to ſaye. He that ſhall eate my fleſſhe, and drynke my bloud: ſhall haue euerlaſtynge
<pb facs="tcp:4069:60"/> lyfe. Now ye ſee y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lyfe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtyng, is the ende of them bothe, therfore they are of one ſtrength, and differ no iote, as touching theyr end. Yf ye gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t them both to geue one gyfte, &amp; to preache one thyng, whereby accordyng to the doctryne of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſcripture to be equal, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of you, why bit ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth not wyth truth to cal the water bloud, aſwell as the bread thee bodye, but that ye iudge to be farre out of frame, and very ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſurde to be ſpoken and no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel at al though ye ſo iudge, for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aſmoche as ye vnderſtande the one, and not the other, for yf ye vnderſtode y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> breaking of bread to be thee ſygne that preacheth to our conſcience the breakyng of hys body, as ye vnderſtand the water to be a ſygne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ar
<pb facs="tcp:4069:61"/> waſhed in chriſtes bloud, then wold ye not thus ymagine, but becauſe ye wil not admyt the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crament of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> body to be a ſigne or toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the crucified body of chriſt but rather the very body it ſelf makyng the ſigne to be y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> thing ſignified, therfore y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of thys word ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> cauſe of this youre forged leſynge, fauoure not ſo moch your enemy whyche more deliteth at your death, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſo you lyue &amp; enioye good dayes, ſuffer him not thus to corrupte both your grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> good ſede offered thervnto w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his moſt pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; infectuous tares of vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>beliefe his treaſure that furniſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſheth the ſtynki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g gulffe of hel, hys inheritaunce, leſt ye at the coming of the huſbandma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is to purge hys corne &amp; gather it together into the gar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nard
<pb facs="tcp:4069:61"/> be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chaffe &amp; weed burned in vnque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cheable fyer, Receyue the lyghte that ye maye walke therein, for he that walkethe in darkenes knoweth not wyther to goo. S. Auſtyne hath geuen you thys glaſſe to plucke oute y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> moote out of youre eyes, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cauſeth you to wynke at truth, &amp; thus craftely to ſhut it vppe in hoodymocke, becauſe the pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rel ſhuld not ſo ouergrow your eyes, that whan ſhame compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth you to ſee, ye cannot ſee, ſo moch is thys godly father and auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wryter your frend, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt viſibile ſign um inuiſibilis gratiae.</hi> That is to ſay A ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is a vilible ſigne, of an inuiſible grace, that is, a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is viſyble, a ſigne of an inuiſible grace &amp; in another pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce he calleth it <hi>Signu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſancti rei.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4069:62"/> That is to ſaye. A ſygne of an holy thyng, the ſygne of an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thyng. As for an example wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter is a viſible thyng ſubiected to the ſenſes of man to ſee, fele, and taſte, whoſe propertie is to mundify and ſcoure the corrup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, and froth that hangeth v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon our viſyble fleſhe, &amp; to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke pure oure outward ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> our eye beyng iudge thereof is certifyed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is cleane &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> oute ſpotte, which water for theſe na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiue qualities, being a thing ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne with our eye is inſtituted of god to be a ſacrament or ſygne to preach an inuiſible grace not ſene w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our bodely eyes, nameli y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> propertie of chriſtes precious bloudſhed for our rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption, &amp; ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> only lauacre of our ſoule by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is eſcoured fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſyn y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo hath feſtered it to deth?
<pb facs="tcp:4069:62"/> our only hyloe which hath clen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed our leproſy that had ſo enfe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bled our weake ſperit ſo y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> we ar now regenerate into the lyuely hope of lyfe euerlaſtyng by the bloud of this vndefiled la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be in ſoch ſort now, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyl wold lay aſſault vnto our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of diſperacion to make oure hope faynte y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> we haue broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lawe, &amp; therfore muſt of force be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned, or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god is vnable to remyt our ini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quities yf we repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t neuer ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re, we haue to va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quiſhe hys ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannous perſuacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s this ꝓmy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes annexed vnto theſe viſyble ſygnes or ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, which ar only ſene w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> eyes of our faith &amp; taſted with ſoule, nameli that <note place="margin">Roma. x<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> chriſt is y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> fulfilling of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> law to iuſtify al y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> beleue, agayn, chriſt hath put out y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> handwryting y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4069:63"/> was agaynſt vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceaued in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lawe writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; that hath he take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the way, &amp; hath faſtened it to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> croſſe, &amp; hath ſpoyled ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le <note place="margin">C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ii</note> &amp; power, &amp; hathe triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his own perſon. And laſt of al paul ſayth, that we ar <note place="margin">Roma, vi</note> not now vnder the law but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der grace, for it is wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to the only conſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; comfort of al afflicted co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, that willing<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theyr wickednes That chriſt for no other purpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe <note place="margin">i, Timo. i</note> came into thys world but to ſaue ſynners. For he hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed hym ſelf to be ſoch a god, ſo mercyful ſo kynd, &amp; louinge to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> repent theyr wickednes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wyl not reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre theyr iniqui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties which they haue wroughte but they ſhal lyue becauſe of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ryghtuouſneſſe that he hathe wroughte. And therfore, thus wryteth Ezechiel the prophet of
<pb facs="tcp:4069:63"/> of him euen in hys own perſon ſpeaking. As truly as I liue, I <note place="margin">Ezech, 33</note> haue no pleaſure in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deth of a ſynner, but moch rather y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked turne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his way &amp; lyue, &amp; to declare his mercy how it lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth to ſee al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaued beholde how frendely he ſpeaketh vnto <note place="margin">Ierem. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</note> Iſrael ſaying. Returne o thou rebel fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſyn, &amp; I wyl not turne my face from the, for I wyl not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be angry wyth the for euer. Thus ye ſe good brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, howe mercifully y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> almyghtyeſt hath wrought wyth vs mortal crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> beyng but duſt &amp; aſſhes, that it hath pleaſed his diuyne maieſtie, ſo moch to te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der oure weake ſperites co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſed about wythe the pryſon &amp; infectuous dongion of fleſſhe and bloude, that in the receyte of thys vyſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble ſygnes, we haue wherwyth to comfort ſtrengthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; augme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb facs="tcp:4069:64"/> augme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t our hope to ſaluacion, namely y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> promiſes of his moſt ſacred worde, which neuer fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> faythful y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> aſſuredly tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth therin, for god is y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> word, &amp; the word is god, And as god is an euerlaſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g god w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out begin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng &amp; without end, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo this word is a perpetual word, &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dureth for euer: For he hath ſayd y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; earth ſhal periſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhe &amp; come to ruynne, but y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lorde endureth for euer Wherfore as y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lord in this viſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble ſacramentes hath preached vnto vs y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> inuiſible grace mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy &amp; fauour of his ſperit, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo with his ſpiritual co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſene with our fleſheli eyes hath he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fyrmed y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> hope of our fore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fathers in the promyſes of hys holy word by viſyble ſignes or ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. As for an example
<pb facs="tcp:4069:64"/> it pleaſed our heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father to leaue vnto Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with certayn ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices in moyſes law to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes &amp; toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhuld be led, as it were by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to Chriſt of al fleſhe, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> truſteth in him y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> only ſauiour. That as the ſacrifices of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Iewes done with bloud wherwyth al thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple was ſprinkeled being a viſyble ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto theyr mortal eyes, preached the inuiſible grace of the promes y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Eſaye propheſied, namely that god wold ſend a lambe ſo pure, innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; ſymple into the earth that butter ſhuld not melt i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his mouth, neyther yet he ſhuld be able to breake a rede, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hys wyl was to be ſlayne, a ſatiſfac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>torye &amp; perfyghte ſacrifyce, for mans tranſgreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; remyſſion
<pb facs="tcp:4069:65"/> of his ſyns. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſytion was a viſible ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fyr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this inuiſyble grace. That god the father had prepa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an inſtrument to cut away y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> froth &amp; corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al that iſſued out of hys loynes, which inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is <note place="margin">Rom. iiii</note> Chriſt the promyſed ſeede to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in whome all nacyons be bleſſed. Therfore as it is euy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by the ſcripture theyr ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes were of equal force with ours, ſauing that theyrs prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vnto them the commynge of Chriſte, and ours, that chriſt is all ready come and is aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded aboue the cloudes to geue ſaluacion vnto men, but all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge to truth hath taught Ieſus to be our peace offeryng and ſatiſfaction. Thus is mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten Luthers opynyon wyth all
<pb facs="tcp:4069:65"/> hys ſcholers in this poynt chief<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fely reproued that yf the bodye of Chriſt ſhulde really be in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the alter <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>as featly ye name it, then were not the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cramentes of equal force, But we only poſſeſſe thys Chriſte of whom theyr ſacramentes teſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed and not they, &amp; conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that we only ar ſaued, becau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe we ar only pertakers of this body, and not they, for theyr ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ledde vnto chriſt, and our Sacrament is (as ye ſaye) Chriſt hym ſelf, O blaſphemye moſt horrible, that the precious bloude of Chriſte oure ſauiour vnyuerſallye ſhedde for all fleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhe, ſhall thus by youre mooſte deuylyſſhe Imagynacyon, be made inſuffycyente? Thynke you that truethe can thus be
<pb facs="tcp:4069:66"/> thus be outfaced of your here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye, no it wyl co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pne your wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kednes iuſtely &amp; proue you as ye ar vntrue in dede. And for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> proffe of thys. What meaneth the mercye ſeate to be placed v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the arke, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> two cherubins to be ſet vpon this mercy ſeate one agaynſt another, &amp; both lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king down into the mercyſeate But that our forefathers, abra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Iſaac, &amp; Iacob, which ſlepte many a daye before chriſtes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by fayth aſſured them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues to be purifyed in the pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cious deth &amp; croſſe of chriſt our ſauiour &amp; of theyr wretchednes, in him to haue fre remiſſion, ſo that ther by euydently it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, that theyr ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes &amp; ours are of one force, &amp; as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching theyr end they dyffer not for aſwel theyr ſacramentes as
<pb facs="tcp:4069:66"/> ours preache Chriſt crucifyed, whych wyth the onely ſacrifyce of hys body hath made al them perfecte for euer, whom he hath ſanctified. That ye may therfo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re vnderſtande this example of the lawe, marke dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly what it ſignifieth that thereby youre hartes maye be opened to bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue thee mooſte ſacred worde of God thee ioyefull tydynges of youre delyueraunce from deth thorowe. Chriſt Ieſus. The ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke fygured the law, which with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>oute parcialitie condempnethe all fleſſhe for ſynne, ſo that ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by could no man be made rygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuous, nether yet ſafe from the vyalles of Goddes wrathefull indignacion whome he powred as a iuſte rewarde, vpon Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s dyſobedyence for after that he hadde preuaricate thys lawe.
<pb facs="tcp:4069:67"/> Eate of all y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> frute wythin this garden, only excepted the frute of knowledge, of good &amp; euell, ſtraythforth wyth the appel, he deuoured death and dampna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, and coulde noo longer be herbored vnder the pleſant ſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dow of the fruteful trees of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, but was bannyſſhed thee preſens of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lord his god with gliſtering ſwordes of flaminge fyer as a traytour moſt rebelli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous, &amp; diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t agaynſte hys law. Now wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> law beyng by nature an exacte iudge &amp; one y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> vſeth noo percialitye in rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding euery one accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to his deſertes, had for ſyn diſhereted Adam, &amp; throwe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym into thys mooſt wretched vale of all my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, wher the curſe of god with oute all reſyſtaunce came vpon hys head, he coulde not for ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me
<pb facs="tcp:4069:67"/> ſeke frendſhyp of the lawe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whoſe ſtraytenes he had taſted and ſo well knewe to abhorre, hate, and condempne ſynne, for the lawe entreateth no man fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dely, but hym which diligently obſerueth all thing wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in, to whom it hath made thys promes, that yf he ſhall doo all thynges conteyned therein he ſhall lyue in them and ſee good daies, but yf he breake this law and let the couenauntes therof be vndone, then wyll the Lorde beuyſe agaynſte hym thys pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges followynge for the abbrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thereof, he wyll vyſyte hym ſhortely with feuers &amp; ſwellin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which ſhal deſtroy y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> eyes &amp; <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etif, xvi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and, xxvi Ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>: xviii Deut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 28.</note> conſume away the hart (y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> is to ſay) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule which hath ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt this law, ſhal dye y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> deth, Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore for aſmoche as he
<pb facs="tcp:4069:68"/> dyſobeyed the ſtatutes of thys lawe was nowe ouerwhelmed wyth deathe, and darkenes ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge no frynde that wolde or coulde be found that was able to bruſte thee intollerable and mooſte paynefull yocke of thee lawe, whych hadde ſo greuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye wounded his conſcye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll ſoche tyme that God of his mere benygnytye, (not wylling that the adueyſarye ſhuld poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe the creature, whom he had made to magnifye hys name,) ſpared not hys onely begotten ſonne Ieſus Chriſte, to make hym partaker of oure vyle fleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhe and all naturall infyrmyti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es therof ſynne excepte, that by hys gloryous death and reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectyon, he myghte treade hym vnder fote which hadde power ouer deathe, and delyuer them
<pb facs="tcp:4069:68"/> that ſate in darkenes &amp; in thee ſhadowe of death from this ter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryble captyuyte, and bynde vp the woundes of Adam and hys poſteritie becauſe therfore that the lawe by the meane of diſobe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dience hadde couered all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde wyth dampnation, he ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me as a lambe mooſt innocente and by hys obedience vnto the death of the croſſe he exempted not onely al men from the curſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of the lawe, but alſo he coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them wythe ſaluacyon that wythout wauerynge truſted in hym, and therefore he is called the mediator of God and ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in thee holye ſcripture, becauſe he beyng bothe God and man not onely ſatiſfied the lawe, but al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo mollyfyed the anger of God hys father, conceyued agaynſte Adam for thee trangreſſyon of
<pb facs="tcp:4069:69"/> the law, for it was not one natu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re I meane man, that was able and of power too obſerue thys law of hys proper ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, ſyns that the lawe hathe confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded ſynne from the begynning, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Adam an al fleſhe that iſſued oute of hys loynes, was ſhutte in, but of neceſſitie there muſt ſome ſoch one be founde, whych beyng coupled together two natures &amp; wythout ſpot of ſynne, ſhuld ſatiſfye for ſynne &amp; pleaſe god for tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy therfore pytyfully lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting the fal of Adam and very Loth to ſee thee Image of God thus bondaged to death, by the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll entycemente of thee cruell ſerpente, and an outcaſte by the lawe, for aſmoche as it percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in earthe, thee impotencye of fleſhe and bloud, how weake
<pb facs="tcp:4069:69"/> &amp; vnable it was to breake thys ſerpentes head, it anoynted eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſte Ieſus to preache good tydynges vnto thee poore, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge vppe the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded hartes and delyuer thee captyues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <note place="margin">Eſaye, 61,</note> deth deſtroyng that had power ouer death, that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kynd might be made a ryghtuous planting of the Lorde for hym to reioyſe in. Chriſt therfore nothinge re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious vnto the wyl of hys fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, who thorow hys fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mercy had apoynted hym a ſauiour before the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the world were leyed, came and was incarnate for our ſake ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iected vnto all oure myſeryes wythoute ſynne that by the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifyce of hys moſt precious bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy myght become a refuge and baſtilio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto al faythfull &amp; pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent ſynners, that beleued in him
<pb facs="tcp:4069:70"/> ſo ſure and ſtronge, that the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyce of the lawe ſhuld not hurt them, that were marked wythe hys bloude, neyther yet the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtes whom the ſtarre let out of the botomles pyt, ſhuld wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke theyr commyſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon them nor ſpue out the deuyſed venge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aunce of thee God of Iacob a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt <note place="margin">Apoca, ix.</note> them, which he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed to fall vpon al fleſhe that hadde not the ſeale of this lam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be in theyr fore headdes. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is he called in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, our mercyſeat for aſmoch as all they that beleue in hym, are defended by hys bloudſhed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge, Nowe is chriſte become oure peace offering and perfect ſacryfyce: our mediator and on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye aduocate, whych hath dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered vs from vnder the lawe, and graffed vs in lybertye and
<pb facs="tcp:4069:70"/> grace, beynge ſo fyrmely &amp; ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a merſyate, that he not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtandeth betwene vs and the lawe, but alſo aſſureth the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubyns of an euerlaſtyng ſeate whych neuer ſhal decaye becau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe they haue hooped in hym, for theſe Cherubyns ſat face to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce vpon the mercyſeate, ſygny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyeth the fathers, and theyr of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpryng that haue ſlept from the creacion of the world vntyl the mooſte gloryous death of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte Ieſus. And all theſe that ſhall ſlepe tyll the apperaunce of the ſonne of man in hys glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye at the conſummation. And theyr lokynge downe into thee mercyſeat, ſygnifieth the confeſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyon of theyr fayth, that they in hym are both holye and ryghtu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſe for aſmoch as vnfaynedly they beleued that, that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes
<pb facs="tcp:4069:71"/> haue teſtyfyed, that as <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u, 13</note> many as truſt in him ſhal haue remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theyr ſyn, for ther is no helth in any other, nether is ther any other name geuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherby they myght be ſaued, but only y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of Ieſu Chriſt, In concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the fathers &amp; we, hooly cleue vnto this chriſt, for aſmoche as in him we haue life euerlaſting &amp; without hym ther ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> come no ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for he is y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer thereof as wytneſſethe hys owne ſperit, ſaying. <hi>Ego do vita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouibus meis.</hi> That is to ſay, I geue lyfe to my ſhepe. Wherfo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re paul to declare y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the fathers which ſlepe in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lord, to haue ea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſame body &amp; haue dronke of the ſame cup which is preached vnto vs in thys Sacramente
<pb facs="tcp:4069:71"/> whereof we alſo are partakers ſayeth, we haue al dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke of one ſpyrytuall rocke, and ar parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of one bread, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ar made one body. <hi>Et hic erat ille panis qui de celo deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dit ex quo, Si quis ederit viuet in aeternum.</hi> That is to ſaye. And this was that bread that came from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, wherof, yf any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, he ſhall lyue for euer. Why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is the head of the faythfull congregacion, Euen Chriſt the mediator betwene god and ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in whom as many as faythful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleue ar buryed from theyr ſynnes, and ryſen agayne wyth hym in newnes of lyfe, and he that doubte the not thys, but wythe an aſſured affyaunce ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peth thereafter, hathe alreadye eaten hys body and dronke hys
<pb facs="tcp:4069:72"/> bloude and hath in hym lyfe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtynge. Contrarye he that beleueth not the mooſte ſacred and eternall Teſtament, ſancti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyed in hys moſt precious blou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, but caſtethe it behynde hys backe as a word doubteful and not to bee truſted, let hym eate thys ſacrament fyue thouſand tymes where in ye fayne more lyke infydels tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faythful chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtians the body of chriſt our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour to be conteyned really, it ſhall aſmoche auaylle hym to ſaluatyon as a dyrgies peny or a maſſe of requiem, for it is not thee ſacramentall eatynge that geueth the ſaluation, but to be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue goddes worde, that is the ſauegarde of the ſoule, neyther is it the Sacramental eatynge that condempnethe thy ſoule, but the vnbeliefe of gods word
<pb facs="tcp:4069:72"/> couereth the wythe death. For the eatynge of the Sacrament wythout fayth in the promeſſe aduexet there vnto, profytethe nothyng, but to eate the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente and ſtedfaſtlye to beleue the promes, he receaueth not on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly the Sacrament, worthelye, but hath alſo lyfe euerlaſtynge not for eatynge the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t but becauſe he beleueth in hym whom the ſacrament fygureth, who is lyfe euerlaſtynge as Io<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>han wytneſſeth ſayinge. God hath geuen vs lyfe euerlaſting and thys lyfe is in hys ſon, he that hathe the ſonne, hath lyfe, and he that hathe not the ſonne of God, hathe not lyfe in hym, Wherfore to eate thys Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">i, Ioh, v.</note> reuerently accordynge to the holye ſcripture, is in brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge of the breade to preache,
<pb facs="tcp:4069:73"/> vnto our conſcyence the lordes deathe, by whom we are ſealed vnto redemption, And in drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng of the cuppe, that is in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyng to hys worde, to haue re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſſyon of all oure iniquities, and lyfe euerlaſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. Now good brethren, becauſe I wyll not be tedious, I hartelye deſyre you in the Lord Ieſus, &amp; yf by hys death &amp; bloudſhedinge ye haue receyued the hope of ſaluacyon do alſo requyre you not, as one hauyng any auctorytye of hym ſelf, but as an inſtrument now<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtered by the louynge kindnes of god to cal you from your he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reſye, to conſyder the Embace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour &amp; hye preſt of our profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſt Ieſus beyng y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> brightnes of gods glory &amp; the very Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of his ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, bearyng vp al thinges w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> word of his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer how he hath in his own per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon
<pb facs="tcp:4069:73"/> purged our ſynnes &amp; is ſet on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rightha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the maieſtie on hye, being eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as moch more ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>celle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> angels, &amp; alſo howe he hath ſanctified y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in his precious bloud to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble helth &amp; ſpiritual reioyſinge of al theſe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> couet y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> immutable or euerlaſtyng heritage attay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by chriſt, for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtedfa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte fayth in his bloud hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> adoptiue heyres of god, in the whych teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ye may euy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly perceaue, yf the burden of ſyn hath not ſeduced you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> grace of god, how this adulteri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>an lerning, I wold ſaye, Luthe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rian doctryne is reproued ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by, beinge the promyſed ſperite of truth ſent of god to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> truſt in his name, the diſpicing of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> killeth the ſoules drawing vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the cur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes of god &amp; hys hateful
<pb facs="tcp:4069:74"/> vengeaunce as is manyfeſt in the holy ſcripture ſpoken, both in the lawe and by the holy pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phetes, for what a grieffe was it vnto Moyſes, whan the chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael wolde not heare hym, neyther beleue the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge from thee Lorde theyr God, whych he brought, thynke you that it petyed hym not to ſe the worde of hys maieſtie in ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le regarde, yea trulye but howe moche more ſhall it greue thee lyuynge God whych of fauour humbled his onely ſonne chriſt Ieſus vnto death, for the ſaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kynd to ſe the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed Teſtament of hys kyndnes towardes vs, and mooſt heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſperyt ſo lytle eſtemed pronu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced by hym, whych far excedeth Moyſes in worthynes and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour euen Ieſus Chriſt. Thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke
<pb facs="tcp:4069:74"/> you that he<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuffer truth thus to looſe his honour and be euel entreated at the handes of fleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhe &amp; bloud, no truly he can, for it abhorreth hys nature, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore he withdraweth not his in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dignacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ſuffereth it, roote the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the earth that diſpyſe it. And to thys deareth the Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phete <note place="margin">Eſay. ii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Eſaye wytnes, ſayinge. Becauſe they haue offended the law, chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged the ordynaunce &amp; made the euerlaſting Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of none effecte. Therfore ſhal y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> curſe deuoure the earth for they that dwel theron haue ſynned &amp; kyndled the wrath of the holye one of Iſrael, which ſhal ſo ſmy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te the hylles that y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> karcaſes of the vngodly ſhal lye in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſtrete for becauſe thei haue neglected this worde (ſayth Ieremye) the Lord wyl ſend vpon the ſword,
<pb facs="tcp:4069:75"/> honger &amp; peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s for he hath al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ready prepared hym ſelf agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt <note place="margin">Ierem, 29</note> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to battaile, &amp; ſet vp y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> power of his voyce to declare hys ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible arme, with his angry cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, yea &amp; the flamme of the conſumyng fyer, whom he hath made both large wide and depe the noryſhing wherof is wodde innumerable, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the breath of the almyghtyeſt ſhal kyndle as <note place="margin">Eſay, 30,</note> a ſmatche of brymſtone, what moued the lorde to threaten the vngodlye that he wolde make heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto them as Iron, and the earth as braſſe that it ſhuld not bryng forth her encreaſe to theyr ſuſtentacion? thee diſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng of hys worde, what prouo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked hym to ſende wylde beaſtes to deuoure them, &amp; make wayſt theyr landes? the deſpyſynge of hys worde, what cauſed him to
<pb facs="tcp:4069:75"/> to ſend a ſword, &amp; a conſuming peſtylens vpon thee ſtubburne to auenge hys Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tempt of it, what drewe the wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull plage of penure vpon them, ſo that they eate the fleſhe of theyr ſonnes and doughters and cauſeth the ſoule of the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de to abhorre them, The deſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng of goddes word: wherfore as Paule ſayth, we ought to ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue the more hede vnto thynges whych we haue herde, leſt we pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryſſhe, for yf the worde whyche was ſpoken by angels was ſted<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>faſt, &amp; euery trangreſſion &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obediens receaued a iuſt recom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pence, how ſhal we eſcape yf we deſpyſe ſo great a ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che (after it was begonne of the Lorde hym ſelfe to be preached) was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fyrmed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> herd it, god heari<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g witnes ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vnto,
<pb facs="tcp:4069:76"/> wythe tokens wonders &amp; diuerſe powers &amp; gyftes of the holy ghoſte accordynge to hys owne wyl, forget not good bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, how ſore y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lorde was but to reueng the diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the cruel Pharao, &amp; the wonderful plages that his ſoule had dyui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed agaynſte hym ſoo heynous they were &amp; intollerable, that y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> poore beaſtes of the fylde &amp; fyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes of the ſee, yea the hole land was layd waſt &amp; became a wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes, for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſyn of thys kynge Egypt moſt horrible in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſyght of god, namely the deſpycynge of hys worde. Cal to your reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>braunce the continuall captiuy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie &amp; moſt fylthy deth that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to paſſure the ſon of Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>merchief in the houſe of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lorde for the contempt of gods word <note place="margin">Ierem, xx</note> preached of Ieremy the lordes
<pb facs="tcp:4069:76"/> Prophete, where Ioſyas, Ico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias, &amp; the falſe prophet Hana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nas which wyth ſoch vyolence reproued the prophet, &amp; caſt the word of the lord behynde theyr backes preſerued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perell, no truely, for the lord co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded the earth by the mouthe of hys prophet that theyr names ſhuld be wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among the outlawes that in theyr life they might ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue no proſperite, &amp; that none of theyr ſeede ſhuld be ſo happy as to ſyt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the leate of dauid, or beare rule in Iuda, but ſhulde moſt ſhamefully dye amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the Babylonians. Syns therfore god of his mere benignite hath left in hys moſt bleſſed word, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> intreature of ſoch rebellions y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hath ſo frowardli deſpiſed their own ſaluacion, &amp; wyllingly for ſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr lord, &amp; creator in that
<pb facs="tcp:4069:77"/> they haue preſumptuouſly ſet y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wytles Imaginacion of duſt &amp; aſhes to contempne the wyſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the god of Iacob, the creator of the whole world, in whoſe ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des ſtandeth the borders &amp; coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes therof to rule it as his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte godly wyll is: only for loue ſake, that we therof ſhuldbe nor tered, &amp; take a diſſiplyne not to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myt any ſoch offence againſt Chriſt our ſauiour, leſt as they came to naught, ſo we peryſſhe in our giltines, Turne therfore good brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your ſtubbur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes &amp; reſyſt not hys holy word, whych is of power ſo myghty &amp; ſtrong that he is able wyth the breath therof to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume you as lyghtly as fyer dothe drye kyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes or ſtubble but rent and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re your hartes &amp; dayly bewayle your ſyn, magnifieng the liuin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge
<pb facs="tcp:4069:77"/> God thorowe your aduocate &amp; mediator Ieſus chriſt that hys longe ſufferance whiche loueth not to ſee your deſtruction, but rather that ye repent, and lyue hath ſo long wythhold the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent arme &amp; wrathful, diſpleaſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re of our heauenly father from you that ſodayn deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had not deuoured you in your wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, ſuffer not this hys mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyfull fauoure to cauſe you to be more careles than the foules of the ayre for the ſtorke know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ethe hys apyoynted tyme, the Turtyl, the ſwalowe, and thee crane, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyder the tyme of theyr trauell, ſhulde not then the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of God, both know &amp; feare y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> tyme of the lordes vengeau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce? Now therfore yf ye wylbe thee ſhepe of hys paſture, and bee
<pb facs="tcp:4069:78"/> be fed of hys ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teouſnes, har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not your hartes as the heddi people dyd in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wyldernes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uokynge thorowe your diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diens the God of al mekenes in hys heauy diſpleaſure to ſwere vnto you as he dyd vnto them, whych there were ouerthrowen for theyr ſynnes, ye ſhal not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into my reſte, but gentyllye heare the voyce of your ſheper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, (as is thee prophecie of hys choſen ſhepe) ſo louingly ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge thus vnto your conſcien<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce. Chyldren yf ye wyll receaue my wordes &amp; kepe my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal you vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the feare of the lord &amp; fynd out the knowledge of god, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalt thou vnderſtand rightuouſnes iudgement &amp; equitie and euery good pathe, for therby wyſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> entereth into your hartes, who <note place="margin">Proue, ii,</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:4069:78"/> by counſel, &amp; vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerueth you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the euyl way &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpeaketh froward thynges. And therfore the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet dauid ſaythe, Bleſſed is y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whych ſeketh after the teſty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monyes of the lord &amp; diligently obeyeth the word of god, whom he hath ſente to heale them &amp; to <note place="margin">Pſal, 17,</note> delyuer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that delyghteth therin. To this ſtaf dyd Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; al hys poſteritie, (than were ſanctified in the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſed ſeede euen Chriſt Ieſus) leue vnto, in al aduerſytye, and neuer were dyſceaued of theyr hope, nor forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the lorde in tyme of trouble, for thys worde cauſeth a fountayne of lyuing water to flowe out of theyr bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes that truſt therin &amp; for this haue many tayſted of mockyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſcorgynges, of bondes of
<pb facs="tcp:4069:79"/> of pryſonment were ſtoned, we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re hewen a ſonder, were te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted, were ſtayne wythe thee ſworde, And theſe all thorowe faythe in thys eternall teſtament, attay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in this lyfe not only a good report but haue receyued y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes of the word, life euerlaſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Wherfore denye ſynne and all vngodlynes, &amp; wythout doute ye ſhall not onely haue the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of thys word wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by ye ſhal be able to vanquiſhe all aſſaultes of our mortal ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye the deuyll, but alſo ſhalbe able by it to dyſcerne this your wycked errour and condempne it &amp; wyth a pure hart magnifye the truth of our heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father whych thorowe hys ſonne Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte oure lorde hath perdoned al oure ſynnes and in hym geuen
<pb facs="tcp:4069:79"/> all them that faythfully beleue the breakynge of hys precious bodye, and mooſte gloryous bloudſheddyng vpon the croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe to be the perfyghte ſacryfyce of oure redemptyon, and the on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye attonemente betwene God the father and mannes conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences thee importyble crowne of euerlaſtynge glorye, wythe hym to reioyſe in thee heauenly Kyngdome contynuallye, and thys is thee true and infallyble eatynge of hys body and bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge of hys mooſte precyous bloude thee endeles comforte of oure ſoules, whyche wyll ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſuffer them to ſee death ney<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther corruption, but to be incor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ruptible and of the ſame immor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tall ſubſtaunce that chriſt oure ſauyoure is, not wythſtanding Luthers errour, whom he hath
<pb facs="tcp:4069:80"/> alreadye condempned wyth the promyſed brethe of hys mouth, namelye the ſperit of truth, whom he promyſed all hys faytheful, to leade them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all truth beyng the Teſtament ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed in hys preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bloud the ſoule &amp; only effecte of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demptyon.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4069:80"/>
            <p> ¶ Wherfore the God of peace that brought agayn fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead our lord Ieſus Chriſt y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> greate ſheperde of the ſhepe thorowe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> bloud of the euerlaſtynge teſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mente, make you perfecte in all good workes, to doo hys wyl, workynge in you, that whyche is pleaſaunt in hys ſyght tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe Ieſus Chriſt our lord, to whom be prayſe, honour &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye foreuer and euer. Lette all people ſaye. Amen. Amen.</p>
            <p>¶ God ſaue the Kynge.</p>
            <p>☞ Grace be wyth you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>¶ Yours as charytye byndeth. T. C:</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:4069:81"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4069:81" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ Imprynted at london by Hugh ſyngelto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the ſygne of ſaynt Auguſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne in paules churche yearde</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
